<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Spirals</title>
                <author>Archimedes</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thomas Heath</persName>
                    <resp>translator</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This electronic edition was prepared by Neel Smith, and is licensed under the
                    Creative Commons NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License. Its markup validates
                    against version P5 of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines, and follows the
                    markup conventions of the "Free Greek" project.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This text is based on pages 151-188 of the Dover reprint edition of Heath's
                    original 1897 publication now in the public domain: <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>Thomas Heath</editor>
                            <title>The Works of Archimedes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mineola, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dover</publisher>
                                <date>2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope
                                type="pp">151-188</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- 
                

ON SPIRALS. 



"ARCHIMEDES to Dositheus greeting. 

Of most of the theorems which I sent to Conon, and of 
which you ask me from time to time to send you the proofs, the 
demonstrations are already before you in the books brought to 
you by Heracleides ; and some more are also contained in that 
which I now send you. Do not be surprised at my taking a 
considerable time before publishing these proofs. This has 
been owing to my desire to communicate them first to persons 
engaged in mathematical studies and anxious to investigate 
them. In fact, how many theorems in geometry which have 
seemed at first impracticable are in time successfully worked out! 
Now Conon died before he had sufficient time to investigate 
the theorems referred to ; otherwise he would have discovered 
and made manifest all these things, and would have enriched 
geometry by many other discoveries besides. For I know well 
that it was no common ability that he brought to bear on 
mathematics, and that his industry was extraordinary. But, 
though many years have elapsed since Conon's death, I do not 
find that any one of the problems has been stirred by a single 
person. I wish now to put them in review one by one, 
particularly as it happens that there are two included among 
them which are impossible of realisation* [and which may 
serve as a warning] how those who claim to discover every- 
thing but produce no proofs of the same may be confuted as 
having actually pretended to discover the impossible. 

* Heiberg reads rAoj ft iro0c<r6fji,wa t but F has rAovs, so that the true reading 
is perhaps rlXovs 5t iroriMftcva. The meaning appears to be simply ' wrong.' 



152 ARCHIMEDES 

What are the problems I mean, and what are those of which 
you have already received the proofs, and those of which the 
proofs are contained in this book respectively, I think it proper 
to specify. The first of the problems was, Given a sphere, to find 
a plane area equal to the surface of the sphere ; and this was 
first made manifest on the publication of the book concerning the 
sphere, for, when it is once proved that the surface of any sphere 
is four times the greatest circle in the sphere, it is clear that it 
is possible to find a plane area equal to the surface of the sphere. 
The second was, Given a cone or a cylinder, to find a sphere 
equal to the cone or cylinder ; the third, To cut a given sphere 
by a plane so that the segments of it have to one another an 
assigned ratio ; the fourth, To cut a given sphere by a plane so 
that the segments of the surface have to one another an assigned 
ratio ; the fifth, To make a given segment of a sphere similar to 
a given segment of a sphere* ; the sixth, Given two segments of 
either the same or different spheres, to find a segment of a sphere 
which shall be similar to one of the segments and have its 
surface equal to the surface of the other segment. The seventh 
was, From a given sphere to cut off a segment by a plane so 
that the segment bears to the cone which has the same base as 
the segment and equal height an assigned ratio greater than 
that of three to two. Of all the propositions just enumerated 
Heracleides brought you the proofs. The proposition stated 
next after these was wrong, viz. that, if a sphere be cut by a 
plane into unequal parts, the greater segment will have to the 
less the duplicate ratio of that which the greater surface has to 
the less. That this is wrong is obvious by what I sent you 
before ; for it included this proposition : If a sphere be cut into 
unequal parts by a plane at right angles to any diameter in the 
sphere, the greater segment of the surface will have to the less 
the same ratio as the greater segment of the diameter has 
to the less, while the greater segment of the sphere has to the 
less a ratio less than the duplicate ratio of that whicfc the 



* rb tioBtv r/xa/xo <r</>a/pas rf doOtvri r/Ltd/uart <r<t>alpas 6/uotaxrai, i.e. to make a 
segment of a sphere similar to one given segment and equal in content to 
another given segment. [Cf. On the Sphere and Cylinder, II. 5.] 



ON SPIRALS. 153 

greater surface has to the less, but greater than the sesqui- 
alterate* of that ratio. The last of the problems was also wrong, 
viz. that, if the diameter of any sphere be cut so that the square 
on the greater segment is triple of the square on the lesser 
segment, and if through the point thus arrived at a plane be 
drawn at right angles to the diameter and cutting the sphere, 
the figure in such a form as is the greater segment of the sphere 
is the greatest of all the segments which have an equal surface. 
That this is wrong is also clear from the theorems which I 
before sent you. For it was there proved that the hemisphere 
is the greatest of all the segments of a sphere bounded by an 
equal surface. 

After these theorems the following were propounded con- 
cerning the conef. If a section of a right-angled cone [a 
parabola], in which the diameter [axis] remains fixed, be made to 
revolve so that the diameter [axis] is the axis [of revolution], 
let the figure described by the section of the right-angled cone 
be called a conoid. And if a plane touch the conoidal figure 
and another plane drawn parallel to the tangent plane cut off 
a segment of the conoid, let the base of the segment cut off be 
defined as the cutting plane, and the vertex as the point in which 
the other plane touches the conoid. Now, if the said figure be 
cut by a plane at right angles to the axis, it is clear that the 
section will be a circle ; but it needs to be proved that the 
segment cut off will be half as large again as the cone which has 
the same base as the segment and equal height. And if two 
segments be cut off from the conoid by planes drawn in any 
manner, it is clear that the sections will be sections of acute- 
angled cones [ellipses] if the cutting planes be not at right 
angles to the axis; but it needs to be proved that the 
segments will bear to one another the ratio of the squares on 
the lines drawn from their vertices parallel to the axis to meet 
the cutting planes. The proofs of these propositions are not 
yet sent to you. 

After these came the following propositions about the spiral, 



* (\6yov) nelfrva ?} i)iu6\tov roO, ov {get /c.r.X., i.e. a ratio greater than (the 
ratio of the surf aces) $. See On the Sphere and Cylinder, II. 8. 
+ This should be presumably ' the conoid,' not ' the cone.' 



154 ARCHIMEDES 

which are as it were another sort of problem having nothing 
in common with the foregoing; and I have written out the 
proofs of them for you in this book. They are as follows. If a 
straight line of which one extremity remains fixed be made to 
revolve at a uniform rate in a plane until it returns to the 
position from which it started, and if, at the same time as the 
straight line revolves, a point move at a uniform rate along the 
straight line, starting from the fixed extremity, the point will 
describe a spiral in the plane. I say then that the area 
bounded by the spiral and the straight line which has returned 
to the position from which it started is a third part of the circle 
described with the fixed point as centre and with radius the 
length traversed by the point along the straight line during the 
one revolution. And, if a straight line touch the spiral at the 
extreme end of the spiral, and another straight line be drawn at 
right angles to the line which has revolved and resumed its 
position from the fixed extremity of it, so as to meet the 
tangent, I say that the straight line so drawn to meet it is 
equal to the circumference of the circle. Again, if the revolving 
line and the point moving along it make several revolutions 
and return to the position from which the straight line started, 
I say that the area added by the spiral in the third revolution 
will be double of that added in the second, that in the fourth 
three times, that in the fifth four times, and generally the areas 
added in the later revolutions will be multiples of that added in 
the second revolution according to the successive numbers, 
while the area bounded by the spiral in the first revolution is a 
sixth part of that added in the second revolution. Also, if on 
the spiral described in one revolution two points be taken and 
straight lines be drawn joining them to the fixed extremity of 
the revolving line, and if two circles be drawn with the fixed 
point as centre and radii the lines drawn to the fixed extremity 
of the straight line, and the shorter of the two lines be produced, 
I say that (1) the area bounded by the circumference of the 
greater circle in the direction of (the part of) the spiral included 
between the straight lines, the spiral (itself) and the produced 
straight line will bear to (2) the area bounded by the circum- 
ference of the lesser circle, the same (part of the) spiral and the 



ON SPIRALS. 155 

straight line joining their extremities the ratio which (3) the 
radius of the lesser circle together with two thirds of the excess 
of the radius of the greater circle over the radius of the lesser 
bears to (4) the radius of the lesser circle together with one 
third of the said excess. 

The proofs then of these theorems and others relating to the 
spiral are given in the present book. Prefixed to them, after the 
manner usual in other geometrical works, are the propositions 
necessary to the proofs of them. And here too, as in the books 
previously published, I assume the following lemma, that, if 
there be (two) unequal lines or (two) unequal areas, the excess 
by which the greater exceeds the less can, by being [continually] 
added to itself, be made to exceed any given magnitude among 
those which are comparable with [it and with] one another." 



Proposition 1 . 

If a point move at a uniform rate along any line, and two 
lengths be taken on it, they will be proportional to the times of 
describing them. 

Two unequal lengths are taken on a straight line, and two 
lengths on another straight line representing the times; and 
they are proved to be proportional by taking equimultiples of 
each length and the corresponding time after the manner of 
Eucl. V. Def. 5. 

Proposition 2. 

If each of two points on different lines respectively move along 
them each at a uniform rate, and if lengths be taken, one on each 
line, forming pairs, such that each pair are described in equal 
times, the lengths will be proportionals. 

This is proved at once by equating the ratio of the lengths 
taken on one line to that of the times of description, which 
must also be equal to the ratio of the lengths taken on the other 
line. 



156 ARCHIMEDES 



Proposition 3. 

Given any number of circles, it is possible to find a straight 
line greater than the sum of all their circumferences. 

For we have only to describe polygons about each and then 
take a straight line equal to the sum of the perimeters of the 
polygons. 

Proposition 4. 

Given two unequal lines, viz. a straight line and the circum- 
ference of a circle, it is possible to find a straight line less than 
the greater of the two lines and greater than the less. 

For, by the Lemma, the excess can, by being added a sufficient 
number of times to itself, be made to exceed the lesser line. 

Thus e.g , if c> I (where c is the circumference of the circle 
and I the length of the straight line), we can find a number n 
such that 

n (c l)> I. 

Therefore c I > - - , 

n 

and c > I + - > I. 

n 

Hence we have only to divide I into n equal parts and add 
one of them to I. The resulting line will satisfy the condition. 



Proposition 5. 

Given a circle with centre 0, and the tangent to it at a point 
A, it is possible to draw from a straight line OFF, meeting the 
circle in P and the tangent in F, such that, if c be the circum- 
ference of any given circle whatever, 

FP : OP < (arc AP) : c. 

Take a straight line, as D, greater than the circumference c. 
[Prop. 3] 



ON SPIRALS. 157 

Through draw OH parallel to the given tangent, and 
draw through A a line APH, meeting the circle in P and OH 




in H t such that the portion PH intercepted between the circle 
and the line OH may be equal to D*. Join OP and produce 
it to meet the tangent in F. 

Then FP:OP = AP: PH, by parallels, 



< (arc AP) : c. 

Proposition 6. 

Given a circle with centre 0, a chord AB less than the 
diameter, and OM the perpendicular on AB from 0, it is possible 
to draw a straight line OFP 9 meeting the chord AB in F and the 
circle in P, such that 



where D : E is any given ratio less than BM : MO. 

Draw OH parallel to AB, and BT perpendicular to BO 
meeting OH in T. 

Then the triangles BMO, OBT are similar, and therefore 

BM:MO = OB: BT, 
whence D : E < OB : BT. 

* This construction, which is assumed without any explanation as to how it 
is to be effected, is described in the original Greek thus: "let PH be placed 
(KelffOu) equal to D, verging (vetfowra) towards A." This is the usual phraseology 
used in the type of problem known by the name of veveis. 



158 



ARCHIMEDES 



that 



Suppose that a line PH (greater than BT) is taken such 



D:E=OB:PH, 




and let PH be so placed that it passes through B and P lies on 
the circumference of the circle, while H is on the line OH*. 
(PH will fall outside BT, because PH > ST.) Join OP meeting 
AB in F. 



We now have 



FP : PS = OP : PH 
= OB:PH 



Proposition 7. 

Given a circle with centre 0, a chord AB less than the 
diameter, and OM the perpendicular on it from 0, it is possible 
to draw from a straight line OFF, meeting the circle in P and 
AB produced in F, such that 



where D : E is any given ratio greater than BM : MO. 

Draw OT parallel to AB, and BT perpendicular to BO 
meeting OT in T. 

* The Greek phrase is "let PH be placed between the circumference and the 
straight line (OH) through B." The construction is assumed, like the similar 
one in the last proposition. 



ON SPIRALS. 



159 



In this case, D : E > BM : M 

> OB : BT, by similar triangles. 




Take a line PH (less than BT) such that 
D:E=OB:PH, 

and place PH so that JP, JT are on the circle and on OT respec- 
tively, while HP produced passes through B*. 
Then FP:PB=OP : PH 

= D:E. 

Proposition 8. 

Given a circle with centre 0, a chord AB less than the 
diameter, the tangent at B, and the perpendicular OM from 
on AB, it is possible to draw frcm a straight line OFP, 
meeting the chord AB in F, the circle in P and the tangent in G y 
such that 



where D : E is any given ratio less than BM : MO. 

If OTbe drawn parallel to AB meeting the tangent at B in T, 

BM : MO = OB : BT, 
so that D:E<OB:BT. 

Take a point G on TB produced such that 

D:E=OB :BC, 
whence BO > BT. 

* PH is described in the Greek as vevowav tirl (verging to) the point B. As 
before the construction is assumed. 



160 



ARCHIMEDES 



Through the points 0, T, C describe a circle, and let OB be 
produced to meet this circle in K. 




Then, since BG > BT> and OB is perpendicular to CT, it is 
possible to draw from a straight line OGQ, meeting CT in 
and the circle about OTG in Q, such that OQ = BK*. 

Let OGQ meet AB in F and the original circle in P. 

Now CG.GT=OG.GQ; 

and OF:OG = BT: GT, 

so that OF.GT=OG.BT. 

It follows that 

CG.GT:OF.GT=OG.GQ:OG.BT, 



or 



CG: OF=GQ:BT 

= BK : BT, by construction, 





= BC: OB 




= BC:OP. 


Hence 


OP:OF=BC :CQ, 


and therefore 


PF :OP = BG : BC, 


or 


PF:BG=OP:BC 




= OB :BC 



= D:E. 

* The Greek words used are : " it is possible to place another [straight line] 
GQ equal to KB verging (vctiov<rav) towards 0." This particular vcvvu is 
discussed by Pappus (p. 298, ed. Hultsch). See the Introduction, chapter v. 



OX SPIRALS. 161 



Proposition 9. 

Given a circle with centre 0, a chord AB less than the 
diameter, the tangent at B, and the perpendicular OM from 
on AB, it is possible to draw from a straight line OPGF, 
meeting the circle in P 9 the tangent in G 9 and AB produced in F 9 
such that 



where D : E is any given ratio greater than BM : MO. 

Let OT be drawn parallel to AB meeting the tangent at B 
in T. 

Then D:E>BM:MO 

> OB : BT t by similar triangles. 
Produce TB to so that 

D:E=OB :BC, 
whence BC<BT. 




Describe a circle through the points 0, T 9 G t and produce OB 
to meet this circle in K. 

Then, since TB > BO, and OB is perpendicular to CT> it is 
possible to draw from a line OGQ, meeting CT in G, and the 
H. A. 11 



162 ARCHIMEDES 

circle about OTC in Q, such that GQ = BK*. Let OQ meet 
the original circle in P and AB produced in F. 

We now prove, exactly as in the last proposition, that 
CG:OF=BK:BT 

= BC:OP. 
Thus, as before, 

OP: OF = BC :CG, 

and OP:PF=BC:BG, 

whence PF:BG = OP: BC 

= OB:BC 

= D:E. 



Proposition 1O. 

If Ai,A Zt A B> ...A n be n lines forming an ascending arith- 
metical progression in which the common difference is equal 
to A lt the least term, then 



[Archimedes' proof of this proposition is given above, p. 107- 
9, and it is there pointed out that the result is equivalent to 



COR. 1. It follows from this proposition that 

n.A n * 
and also that 



[For the proof of the latter inequality see p. 109 above.] 

COR. 2. All the results will equally hold if similar figures 
are substituted for squares. 

* See the note on the last proposition. 



ON SPIRALS. 



163 



Proposition 11. 

If A lt A^n.nAn be n lines forming an ascending arith- 
metical progression [in which the common difference is equal to 
the least term -4J*, then 



but 



<A n *:{A n .A 1 +$(A n -A l )*}; 



G 



(n - 1) A n * : (A n _* + A n _* + . . . + A?) 



[Archimedes sets out the terms side by side in the manner 
shown in the figure, where BC = A n> DE = A n _ ly ...RS = A l , and 
produces DE, FG, ...RS until they are 

respectively equal to EC or A n> so that CHI T u 

EH, GI,...SU in the figure are re- 
spectively equal to A lf A 2 ...A n _ lt He 
further measures lengths BK, DL, 
FM, ...PFalong EG, DE, FG,...PQ re- 
spectively each equal to RS. 

The figure makes the relations 
between the terms easier to see with 
the eye, but the use of so large a 

number of letters makes the proof B F p 

somewhat difficult to follow, and it 
may be more clearly represented as follows.] 

It is evident that (A n A t ) = A n ^ lt 
The following proportion is therefore obviously true, viz. 
(n - 1) A* : (n - 1) (A n . A, + A^*) 



V- 



* The proposition is true even when the common difference is not equal to 
A lt and is assumed in the more general form in Props. 25 and 26. But, as 
Archimedes' proof assumes the equality of A 1 and the common difference, the 
words are here inserted to prevent misapprehension. 

112 



164 ARCHIMEDES 

In order therefore to prove the desired result, we have only 
to show that 

( - 1) A n . A t + i (n - 1) A^ < (A n > + A*.? + . . . + A*) 
but > (A+J + An_J +... + Aft 

I. To prove the first inequality, we have 



And 

n _ 1 f +...+^ 2 ' 

. . . + (A, 



+ (n-l)A l t 

A n . 1 + 
+ A, 



A_ 1 ....................................... (2). 

Comparing the right-hand sides of (1) and (2), we see that 
(n 1)A* is common to both sides, and 

(n - 1) A l . A n _ l < n A l . -4 n _ 1( 
while, by Prop. 10, Cor. 1, 



It follows therefore that 



and hence the first part of the proposition is proved. 

II. We have now, in order to prove the second result, to 
show that 

(n - 1) A n . A, + J (n - 1) A^f > (A^ + A^f + . . . +Aft 



ON SPIRALS. 165 

The right-hand side is equal to 



3 + 



A n . 1 ........................ (3). 

Comparing this expression with the right-hand side of (1) above, 
we see that (n 1) A* is common to both sides, and 



while, by Prop. 10, Cor. 1, 

i (n - 1) A n .* > (A^f + A*.? + ...+ A>). 
Hence 



and the second required result follows. 

COR. The results in the above proposition are equally true if 
similar figures be substituted for squares on the several lines. 

DEFINITIONS. 

1. If a straight line drawn in a plane revolve at a uniform 
rate about one extremity which remains fixed and return to 
the position from which it started, and if, at the same time as 
the line revolves, a point move at a uniform rate along the 
straight line beginning from the extremity which remains fixed, 
the point will describe a spiral (2\t|) in the plane. 

2. Let the extremity of the straight line which remains 



166 ARCHIMEDES 

fixed while the straight line revolves be called the origin* 
(dp%d) of the spiral. 

3. And let the position of the line from which the straight 
line began to revolve be called the initial line* in the 
revolution (dp%d ra? 



4. Let the length which the point that moves along the 
straight line describes in one revolution be called the first 
distance, that which the same point describes in the second 
revolution the second distance, and similarly let the distances 
described in further revolutions be called after the number of 
the particular revolution. 

5. Let the area bounded by the spiral described in the 
first revolution and the first distance be called the first area, 
that bounded by the spiral described in the second revolution 
and the second distance the second area, and similarly for the 
rest in order. 

6. If from the origin of the spiral any straight line be 
drawn, let that side of it which is in the same direction as that 
of the revolution be called forward (Trpoayovpeva), and that 
which is in the other direction backward 



7. Let the circle drawn with the origin as centre and the 
first distance as radius be called the first circle, that drawn 
with the same centre and twice the radius the second circle, 
and similarly for the succeeding circles. 



Proposition 12. 

If any number of straight lines drawn from the origin to 
meet the spiral make equal angles with one another, the lines will 
be in arithmetical progression. 

[The proof is obvious.] 

* The literal translation would of coarse be the " beginning of the spiral " 
and " the beginning of the revolution " respectively. But the modern names 
will be more suitable for use later on, and are therefore employed here. 



ON SPIRALS. 167 

Proposition 13. 

If a straight line touch the spiral, it will touch it in one point 
only. 

Let be the origin of the spiral, and BC a tangent to it. 

If possible, let BC touch the spiral in two points P, Q. 
Join OP, OQ, and bisect the angle POQ by the straight line OR 
meeting the spiral in R. 




Then [Prop. 12] OR is an arithmetic mean between OP and 
OQ, or 



But in any triangle POQ, if the bisector of the angle POQ 
meets PQ in K, 

OP + OQ>20#*. 

Therefore OK < OR, and it follows that some point on BC 
between P and Q lies within the spiral. Hence BC cuts the 
spiral; which is contrary to the hypothesis. 

Proposition 14. 

IfObe the origin, and P, Q two points on the first turn of 
the spiral, and if OP, OQ produced meet the 'first circle' 
AKP'Q' in P', Q' respectively, OA being the initial line, then 

OP : OQ = (arc AKP') : (arc AKQ'). 

For, while the revolving line OA moves about 0, the point 
A on it moves uniformly along the circumference of the circle 

* This is assumed as a known proposition ; but it is easily proved. 



168 ARCHIMEDES 

AKP'Q', and at the same time the point describing the spiral 
moves uniformly along OA. 




Thus, while A describes the arc AKP', the moving point on 
OA describes the length OP, and, while A describes the arc 
AKQ', the moving point on OA describes the distance OQ. 

Hence OP : OQ = (arc AKP f ) : (arc AKQ'). [Prop. 2] 



Proposition 15. 

IfP,Q be points on the second turn of the spiral, and OP, 
OQ meet the 'first circle' AKP'Q' in P', Q', as in the last 
proposition, and if c be the circumference of the first circle, then 

OP : OQ = c + (arc AKP') : c + (arc AKQ'). 

For, while the moving point on OA describes the distance 
OP, the point A describes the whole of the circumference of 
the ' first circle ' together with the arc AKP' ; and, while the 
moving point on OA describes the distance OQ, the point A 
describes the whole circumference of the ' first circle ' together 
with the arc AKQ'. 

COR. Similarly, if P, Q are on the nth turn of the spiral, 
OP : OQ - (n - 1) c + (arc AKP') : (n - 1) c + (arc AKQ'). 



ON SPIRALS. 169 



Propositions 16, 17. 

If BG be the tangent at P t any point on the spiral, PC being 
the 'forward* part of BG, and if OP be joined, the angle OPC 
is obtuse while the angle OPB is acute. 

I. Suppose P to be on the first turn of the spiral. 

Let OA be the initial line, AKP' the ' first circle/ Draw 
the circle DLP with centre and radius OP, meeting OA in 
D. This circle must then, in the ' forward ' direction from P, 




fall within the spiral, and in the ' backward ' direction outside 
it, since the radii vectores of the spiral are on the ' forward ' side 
greater, and on the ' backward ' side less, than OP. Hence the 
angle OPG cannot be acute, since it cannot be less than the 
angle between OP and the tangent to the circle at P, which is 
a right angle. 

It only remains therefore to prove that OPC is not a right 
angle. 

If possible, let it be a right angle. BC will then touch 
the circle at P. 

Therefore [Prop. 5] it is possible to draw a line OQC 
meeting the circle through P in Q and BC in (7, such that 

CQ : OQ< (arc PQ) : (arc DLP) (1). 



170 ARCHIMEDES 

Suppose that OC meets the spiral in R and the ' first circle ' 
in R'\ and produce OP to meet the ' first circle ' in P'. 

From (1) it follows, componendo, that 

CO : OQ < (arc DLQ) : (arc DLP) 

< (arc AKR') : (arc AKP') 

< OR : OP. [Prop. 14] 
But this is impossible, because OQ = OP, and OR < OC. 

Hence the angle OPC is not a right angle. It was also 
proved not to be acute. 

Therefore the angle OPC is obtuse, and the angle OPB 
consequently acute. 

II. If P is on the second, or the nth turn, the proof is the 
same, except that in the proportion (1) above we have to 
substitute for the arc DLP an arc equal to (p + arc DLP) or 
(n 1 . p + arc DLP), where p is the perimeter of the circle 




DLP through P. Similarly, in the later steps, p or (n 1) p 
will be added to each of the arcs DLQ and DLP 9 and c or 
(n-l)c to each of the arcs AKR', AKP', where c is the 
circumference of the 'first circle* AKP'. 



ON SPIRALS. 



171 



Propositions 18, 19. 

I. If OA be the initial line, A the end of the first turn of 
the spiral, and if the tangent to the spiral at A be drawn, the 
straight line OB drawn from perpendicular to OA will meet 
the said tangent in some point B, and OB will be equal to the 
circumference of the 'first circle' 

II. If A' be the end of the second turn, the perpendicular 
OB will meet the tangent at A' in some point B', and OB' will 
be equal to 2 (circumference of '' second circle 9 ). 

III. Generally, if A n be the end of the nth turn, and OB 
meet the tangent at A n in B n , then 



where c n is the circumference of the l nth circle. 1 

I. Let A KG be the 'first circle/ Then, since the 'back- 
ward ' angle between OA and the tangent at A is acute [Prop. 
16], the tangent will meet the ' first circle ' in a second point C. 
And the angles CAO, BOA are together less than two right 
angles ; therefore OB will meet AC produced in some point B. 




Then, if c be the circumference of the first circle, we have 
to prove that 

OB = c. 

If not, OB must be either greater or less than c. 



172 ARCHIMEDES 

(1) If possible, suppose OB > c. 

Measure along OB a length OD less than OB but greater 
than c. 

We have then a circle AKC, a chord AC in it less than 
the diameter, and a ratio AO : OD which is greater than the 
ratio AO : OB or (what is, by similar triangles, equal to it) the 
ratio of ^AC to the perpendicular from on AC. Therefore 
[Prop. 7] we can draw a straight line OPF, meeting the circle 
in P and CA produced in F, such that 

FP:PA=AO:OD. 
Thus, alternately, since AO = PO, 

FP:PO = PA :OD 

< (arc PA) : c, 
since (arc PA) > PA, and OD > c. 

Componendo, 

FO : PO < (c + arc PA) : c 

<OQ:OA, 

where OF meets the spiral in Q. [Prop. 15] 

Therefore, since OA = OP, FO < OQ ; which is impossible. 
Hence OB $ c. 

(2) If possible, suppose OB < c. 

Measure OE along OB so that OE is greater than OB but 
less than c. 

In this case, since the ratio AO : OE is less than the ratio 
AO : OB (or the ratio of \AG to the perpendicular from 
on AC), we can [Prop. 8] draw a line OF'P'G, meeting AC in 
F', the circle in F, and the tangent at A to the circle in G, 
such that 

F'P':AG = AO:OE. 

Let OP'G cut the spiral in Q'. 
Then we have, alternately, 

F'P':P'0 = AG:OE 

> (arc AP') : c, 
because AG > (arc AP'), and OE < c. 



ON SPIRALS. 



173 



Therefore 

F'O : P'O < (arc AKP') : c 

< OQ[ : OA. [Prop. 14] 

But this is impossible, since OA = OP', and OQ' < OF'. 

Hence OB { c. 

Since therefore OB is neither greater nor less than c, 

05 = c. 

II. Let A'K'C' be the 'second circle/ A'C' being the 
tangent to the spiral at A (which will cut the second circle, 
since the 'backward' angle OA'C' is acute). Thus, as before, 
the perpendicular OB' to OA will meet AC' produced in some 
point B'. 

If then c' is the circumference of the 'second circle/ we 
have to prove that OB' = 2c'. 

e 
C' - - 




For, if not, OB' must be either greater or less than 2c'. 
(1) If possible, suppose OB' > 2c'. 

Measure OD' along OB' so that OD' is less than OB' but 
greater than 2c'. 

Then, as in the case of the ' first circle ' above, we can draw 
a straight line OPF meeting the 'second circle' in P and C f A f 
produced in F, such that 



174 ARCHIMEDES 

Let OF meet the spiral in Q. 
We now have, since A'O = PO, 



< (arc A'P) : 2c', 
because (arc AT) > AT and OD' > 2c'. 

Therefore FO : PO < (2c' + arc AT) : 2c' 

< OQ : OA'. [Prop. 15, Cor.] 

Hence FO < OQ] which is impossible. 
Thus OB' $ 2c'. 

Similarly, as in the case of the ' first circle ', we can prove that 

OB'H:2c'. 
Therefore OB' = 2c'. 

III. Proceeding, in like manner, to the 'third* and suc- 
ceeding circles, we shall prove that 



Proposition 2O. 

I: If P be any point on the first turn of the spiral and OT 
be drawn perpendicular to OP, OT will meet the tangent at P to 
the spiral in some point T ; and, if the circle drawn with centre 
and radius OP meet the initial line in K, then OT is equal to 
the arc of this circle between K and P measured in the 'forward 1 
direction of the spiral. 

II. Generally, if P be a point on the nth turn,, and the 
notation be as before, while p represents the circumference of the 
circle with radius OP, 

OT = (nl)p + arc KP (measured 'forward '). 

I. Let P be a point on the first turn of the spiral, OA the 
initial line, PR the tangent at P taken in the 'backward* 
direction. 

Then [Prop. 16] the angle OPR is acute. Therefore PR 



ON SPIRALS. 



175 



meets the circle through P in some point R ; and also OT will 
meet PR produced in some point T. 

If now OT is not equal to the arc KRP, it must be either 
greater or less. 




(1) If possible, let OT be greater than the arc KRP. 
Measure OU along OT less than OT but greater than the 
arc KRP. 

Then, since the ratio PO : OU is greater than the ratio 
PO : OT, or (what is, by similar triangles, equal to it) the 
ratio of ^PR to the perpendicular from on PR, we can draw 
a line OQF, meeting the circle in Q and RP produced in F, 
such that 

FQ:PQ = PO: OU. [Prop. 7] 

Let OF meet the spiral in Q'. 
We have then 



< (arc PQ) : (arc KRP), by hypothesis. 

Componendo, 

FO:QO< (arc KRQ) : (arc KRP) 

< OQ' : OP. [Prop. 14] 

But QO = OP. 



176 ARCHIMEDES 

Therefore FO < OQ' ; which is impossible. 
Hence OT } (arc KRP). 

(2) The proof that OT^ (arc KRP) follows the method of 
Prop. 18, I. (2), exactly as the above follows that of Prop. 18, 



Since then OT is neither greater nor less than the 
it is equal to it. 

II. If P be on the second turn, the same method shows 

that 

OT = p + (a,ro KRP); 

and, similarly, we have, for a point P on the nth turn, 
OT = (n - 1) p + (arc KRP). 

Propositions 21, 22, 23. 

Given an area bounded by any arc of a spiral and the lines 
joining the extremities of the arc to the origin, it is possible to 
circumscribe about the area one figure, and to inscribe in it 
another figure, each consisting of similar sectors of circles, and 
such that the circumscribed figure exceeds the inscribed by less 
than any assigned area. 

For let BC be any arc of the spiral, the origin. Draw 
the circle with centre and radius 0(7, where C is the 'forward* 
end of the arc. 

Then, by bisecting the angle BOG, bisecting the resulting 
angles, and so on continually, we shall ultimately arrive at 
an angle COr cutting off a sector of the circle less than any 
assigned area. Let COr be this sector. 

Let the other lines dividing the angle BOG into equal parts 
meet the spiral in P, Q, and let Or meet it in R. With as 
centre and radii OB, OP, OQ, OR respectively describe arcs of 
circles Bp'> bBq', pQr, qRc', each meeting the adjacent radii as 
shown in the figure. In each case the arc in the 'forward* 
direction from each point will fall within, and the arc in the 
'backward' direction outside, the spiral. 



ON SPIRALS. 



177 



We have now a circumscribed figure and an inscribed figure 
each consisting of similar sectors of circles. To compare their 
areas, we take the successive sectors of each, beginning from 0(7, 
and compare them. 




The sector OCr in the circumscribed figure stands alone. 
And (sector Rq) = (sector ORc'), 

(sector OQp) = (sector OQr), 
(sector OPb) = (sector OPq'\ 
while the sector OBp' in the inscribed figure stands alone. 

Hence, if the equal sectors be taken away, the difference be- 
tween the circumscribed and inscribed figures is equal to the 
difference between the sectors OCr and OBp'\ and this difference 
is less than the sector OCr, which is itself less than any 
assigned area. 

The proof is exactly the same whatever be the number of 
angles into which the angle BOG is 
divided, the only difference being 
that, when the arc begins from the 
origin, the smallest sectors OP6, OPq' 
in each figure are equal, and there is 
therefore no inscribed sector standing 
by itself, so that the difference 
between the circumscribed and in- 
scribed figures is equal to the sector 
OCr itself. 




H. A. 



12 



178 ARCHIMEDES 

Thus the proposition is universally true. 

COR. Since the area bounded by the spiral is intermediate 
in magnitude between the circumscribed and inscribed figures, 
it follows that 

(1) a figure can be circumscribed to the area such that it 
exceeds the area by less than any assigned space, 

(2) a figure can be inscribed such that the area exceeds it by 
less than any assigned space. 

Proposition 24. 

The area bounded by the first turn of the spiral and the 
initial line is equal to one-third of the 'first circle ' [= TT (27ra) 8 , 
where the spiral is r = a0]. 

[The same proof shows equally that, if OP be any radius 
vector in the first turn of the spiral, the area of the portion of 
the spiral bounded thereby is equal to one-third of that sector of 
the circle drawn with radius OP which is bounded by the initial 
line and OP, measured in the 'forward ' direction from the 
initial line.] 

Let be the origin, OA the initial line, A the extremity of 
the first turn. 

Draw the ' first circle/ i.e. the circle with as centre and 
OA as radius. 

Then, if Ci be the area of the first circle, R^ that of the first 
turn of the spiral bounded by OA, we have to prove that 



For, if not, S^ must be either greater or less than C l9 

I. If possible, suppose JRj < $C lt 

We can then circumscribe a figure about R^ made up of 
similar sectors of circles such that, if F be the area of this 

figure, 

F-^fa-K, 

whence F<%C l . 



ON SPIRALS. 



179 



Let OP, OQ, ... be the radii of the circular sectors, beginning 
from the smallest. The radius of the largest is of course OA. 

The radii then form an ascending arithmetical progression 
in which the common difference is equal to the least term OP. 
If n be the number of the sectors, we have [by Prop. 10, Cor. 1] 

n. OA*< 3 (OP' + OQ* + ... + 04 8 ); 




and, since the similar sectors are proportional to the squares on 
their radii, it follows that 

G, < 3P, 



or 



But this is impossible, since F was less than 
Therefore 1 



II. If possible, suppose B^ > ^Q. 

We can then inscribe a figure made up of similar sectors of 
circles such that, if/ be its area, 

whence /> $C lt 

If there are (n 1) sectors, their radii, as OP, OQ, ..., form 
an ascending arithmetical progression in which the least term 
is equal to the common difference, and the greatest term, as 
OF, is equal to (n - 1) OP. 

12-2 



180 ARCHIMEDES 

Thus [Prop. 10, Cor. 1], 

n . OA > 3 ( OP ' + OQ 2 + . . . + Y ' ), 
whence C 1 > 3f, 

or /<*C f I ; 

which is impossible, since /> (7j. 

Therefore J2i H#,. 

Since then 1^ is neither greater nor less than (7 lf 

A = ^. 

[Archimedes does not actually find the area of the spiral 
cut off by the radius vector OP, where P is any point on the 
first turn ; but, in order to do this, we have only to substitute 




in the above proof the area of the sector KLP of the circle 
drawn with as centre and OP as radius for the area C l of 
the ' first circle ', while the two figures made up of similar sectors 
have to be circumscribed about and inscribed in the portion 
OEP of the spiral. The same method of proof then applies 
exactly, and the area of OEP is seen to be J (sector KLP). 

We can prove also, by the same method, that, if P be a 
point on the second, or any later turn, as the wth, the complete 
area described by the radius vector from the beginning up to 
the time when it reaches the position OP is, if C denote the 
area of the complete circle with as centre and OP as radius, 
J (C + sector KLP) or (n^~l . C + sector KLP) respectively. 

The area so described by the radius vector is of course not 
the same thing as the area bounded by the last complete turn 



ON SPIRALS. 181 

of the spiral ending at P and the intercepted portion of the 
radius vector OP. Thus, suppose RI to be the area bounded 
by the first turn of the spiral and OA l (the first turn ending at 
A l on the initial line), R* the area added to this by the second 
complete turn ending at A 2 on the initial line, and so on. ^ has 
then been described twice by the radius vector when it arrives 
at the position OA*\ when the radius vector arrives at the 
position OA 9 , it has described R l three times, the ring JB 2 twice, 
and the ring R 3 once ; and so on. 

Thus, generally, if G n denote the area of the ' nth circle/ we 
shall have 



while the actual area bounded by the outside, or the complete 
nth, turn and the intercepted portion of OA n will be equal to 



It can now be seen that the results of the later Props. 25 
and 26 may be obtained from the extension of Prop. 24 just 
given. 

To obtain the general result of Prop. 26, suppose BC to be 
an arc on any turn whatever of the spiral, being itself less than 
a complete turn, and suppose B to be beyond A n the extremity 
of the nth complete turn, while G is ' forward ' from B. 

Let - be the fraction of a turn between the end of the nth 

2 
turn and the point B. 

Then the area described by the radius vector up to the 
position OB (starting from the beginning of the spiral) is 
equal to 

~ ( circle with 



Also the area described by the radium vector from the beginning 
up to the position OC is 



\( n + 



182 



ARCHIMEDES 



The area bounded by OB, OG and the portion BEG of the 
spiral is equal to the difference between these two expressions ; 
and, since the circles are to one another as OB* to 0(7*, the 
difference may be expressed as 



Jf +\ (i _ 9^\ (circle with rad. OG) + (sector B'MG)\ . 
But, by Prop. 15, Cor., 

L +\ (circle B'MG) : {(+-) (circle B'MG) + (sector B'MC)\ 

= OB : OG, 




so that 



In +) (circle B'MG) : (sector B'MG) = OB:(OC- OB). 

, area BEG _ t (l OB \ /, OB* 

US sector B'M ~ 



OB(OC + OB) + 00" 
*' OC" 

_Qg. 0^ + $(OC -OB)* 
OC* 

The result of Prop. 25 is a particular case of this, and the 
result of Prop. 27 follows immediately, as shown under that 
proposition.] 



ON SPIRALS. 183 



Propositions 25, 26, 27. 

[Prop. 25.] If A* be the end of the second turn of the spiral, 
the area bounded by the second turn and OA 2 is to the area 
of the 'second circle' in the ratio of 7 to 12, being the ratio of 
{rtf*! + (r a rj*} to r*, where r lt r z are the radii of the 'first ' 
and ' second ' circles respectively. 

[Prop. 26.] If BC be any arc measured in the 'forward ' 
direction on any turn of a spiral, not being greater than the 
complete turn, and if a circle be drawn with as centre and OC 
as radius meeting OS in B\ then 

(area of spiral between OB, 00) : (sector OB'C) 

= {00. OB + $(00- OB)*} : OC 9 . 

[Prop. 27.] If RI be the area of the first turn of the spiral 
bounded by the initial line, R 2 the area of the ring added by the 
second complete turn, R 3 that of the ring added by the third turn, 
and so on, then 



Also R 2 

[Archimedes' proof of Prop. 25 is, mutatis mutandis, the 
same as his proof of the more general Prop. 26. The latter 
will accordingly be given here, and applied to Prop. 25 as a 
particular case.] 

Let BO be an arc measured in the ' forward ' direction on 
any turn of the spiral, CKB' the circle drawn with as centre 
and OC as radius. 

Take a circle such that the square of its radius is equal 
to OC. OB + $(OC- OB)*, and let <r be a sector in it whose 
central angle is equal to the angle BOG. 
Thus a : (sector OB'G) = {OC . OB + J (OC - 05)'} : OC*, 
and we have therefore to prove that 

(area of spiral OBC) = cr. 

For, if not, the area of the spiral OBC (which we will call S) 
must be either greater or less than cr. 



184 



ARCHIMEDES 



I. Suppose, if possible, 8 r. 

Circumscribe to the area 8 a figure made up of similar 
sectors of circles, such that, if F be the area of the figure, 

F-Sr-S, 
whence F<<r. 

Let the radii of the successive sectors, starting from OB, 
be OP, OQ,...OC. Produce OP, OQ,... to meet the circle 
0KB',... 




If then the lines OB, OP, OQ, ... OC be n in number, the 
number of sectors in the circumscribed figure will be (n 1), 
and the sector OB'G will also be divided into (n 1) equal 
sectors. Also OB, OP, OQ, ...OC will form an ascending 
arithmetical progression of n terms. 

Therefore [see Prop, 11 and Cor.] 
(n - 1) 0(7* : (OP 8 + OQ 2 + .. . + OCT) 

< OC* :{OC.OB + $(OC- OB)*} 

< (sector OB'C) : <r, by hypothesis. 
Hence, since similar sectors are as the squares of their radii, 

(sector OB'C) : F< (sector OB'C) : <r, 
so that F > <r. 

But this is impossible, because F <<r. 
Therefore 



ON SPIRALS. 185 

II. Suppose, if possible, S > a. 

Inscribe in the area 8 a figure made up of similar sectors of 
circles such that, if /be its area, 

flf _/<_,, 

whence f><r. 

Suppose OB, OP, ... F to be the radii of the successive 
sectors making up the figure/ being (n 1) in number. 

We shall have in this case [see Prop. 11 and Cor.] 
(n - 1) OC 2 : (OB 9 + OP 8 + ... + OF 2 ) 

> OC 2 : [OC.OB + $(OC- OB)*}, 
whence (sector OB'C) :/> (sector OB'CT) : <r, 
so that /<<r. 

But this is impossible, because /> <r. 

Therefore S$<r. 

Since then 8 is neither greater nor less than <r, it follows that 

S=<7. 

In the particular case where B coincides with A lt the end 
of the first turn of the spiral, and with A 2 , the end of the 
second turn, the sector OB'C becomes the complete 'second 
circle/ that, namely, with OA 2 (or r z ) as radius. 

Thus 

(area of spiral bounded by OA^) : (' second circle ') 
-{Vi + Jfo-r,) 1 } :r a " 
= (2 + ) : 4 (since r* = 2^) 
= 7 : 12. 

Again, the area of the spiral bounded by 0-4 2 is equal to 
E 1 + -R 2 (i-e. the area bounded by the first turn and OA ly 
together with the ring added by the second turn). Also the 
'second circle 1 is four times the 'first circle/ and therefore 
equal to 12^. 

Hence (Ri + RJ : 121^ = 7 : 12, 

or Ri + Bt^lRi. 

Thus Rt^GRt (1). 



186 ARCHIMEDES 

Next, for the third turn, we have 

(R, + # 2 + .R 3 ) : (' third circle ') = {r s r a + $ (r a - ** 2 ) 2 } 



= 19 : 27, 
and (' third circle ') = 9 (' first circle ') 



therefore J^ + R 2 + R 3 = l9R ly 

and, by (1) above, it follows that 



-2JZ, ............................ (2), 

and so on. 

Generally, we have 

(R 1 + K !l +...+R n ): (nth circle) = (r n r n _, + $("*- '-i) 2 } : r 
( A + .Rj + . . . + Rn-J : (n -^Tth circle) 



and (nth circle) : (n 1th circle) = r n s : r n _! ! . 

Therefore 

(R, + R, + ... + R n ) : (R, + R* + . 



= {3n (re - 1) + 1} : {3 (n - l)(n - 2) + 1}. 
Dirimendo, 



-2) + l} ......... (a). 

Similarly 



from which we derive 



ON SPIRALS. 187 

Combining (a) and (/8), we obtain 

n:n-i = (^-l):(rc-2). 
Thus 

JJ 2 > ^s> ^?4> Rn are in the ratio of the successive numbers 
1,2, 3. ..(-!). 

Proposition 28. 

IfObe the origin and BO any arc measured in the 'forward ' 
direction on any turn of the spiral, let two circles be drawn 

(1) with centre 0, and radius OB, meeting 00 in C', and 

(2) with centre and radius 00, meeting OB produced in B'. 
Then, if E denote the area bounded by the larger circular arc 
E'G, ike line B'B, and the spiral EG, while F denotes the area 
bounded by the smaller arc BO', the line CO' and the spiral BO, 

E\F={OB + l(OG-OB)} : {OB + (00 -OB)}. 

Let a- denote the area of the lesser sector OBO f ; then the 
larger sector OB'C is equal to <r + F -f E. 




Thus [Prop. 26] 



whence 

E : (cr + F) = {0(7(0(7 - OB) - (00 - OJS) 2 } 



[OB (00 - OB) + (00 - OB) 2 } 

-OB)'} ............ (2). 



188 ARCHIMEDES ON SPIRALS. 

Again 



F+E) :o- = 0<7: OB*. 
Therefore, by the first proportion above, ex aequali, 

(<r + F) : <r = {OC.OB + $(OC-OBy} : OB', 
whence 

(a- + F) : F= {OC . OB + $ (OG - OB)'} 

:{OB(OC-OB) + $ (OC - OBJ}. 
Combining this with (2) above, we obtain 
E:F={OB (00 - OB) + ) (OC - OB)*} 

: {OB (OC -OB) + $ (OC - OB)"} 
= {OB + 1 (OC - OB)} : {OB + $ (OC - OB)}. 



            -->
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
