<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Conoids and Spheroids</title>
                <author>Archimedes</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thomas Heath</persName>
                    <resp>translator</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This electronic edition was prepared by Neel Smith, and is licensed under the
                    Creative Commons NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License. Its markup validates
                    against version P5 of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines, and follows the
                    markup conventions of the "Free Greek" project.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This text is based on pages 99-150 of the Dover reprint edition of Heath's
                    original 1897 publication now in the public domain: <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>Thomas Heath</editor>
                            <title>The Works of Archimedes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mineola, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dover</publisher>
                                <date>2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope
                                type="pp">99-150</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- 
            
ON CONOIDS AND SPHEKOIDS. 



Introduction *. 

" ARCHIMEDES to Dositheus greeting. 

In this book I have set forth and send you the proofs of the 
remaining theorems not included in what I sent you before, and 
also of some others discovered later which, though I had often 
tried to investigate them previously, I had failed to arrive at 
because I found their discovery attended with some difficulty. 
And this is why even the propositions themselves were not 
published with the rest. But afterwards, when I had studied 
them with greater care, I discovered what I had failed in 
before. 

Now the remainder of the earlier theorems were propositions 
concerning the right-angled conoid [paraboloid of revolution] ; 
but the discoveries which I have now added relate to an obtuse- 
angled conoid [hyperboloid of revolution] and to spheroidal 
figures, some of which I call oblong (Trapapatcea) and others fiat 



I. Concerning the right-angled conoid it was laid down 
that, if a section of a right-angled cone [a parabola] be made to 
revolve about the diameter [axis] which remains fixed and 

* The whole of this introductory matter, including the definitions, is trans- 
lated literally from the Greek text in order that the terminology of Archimedes 
may be faithfully represented. When this has once been set out, nothing will 
be lost by returning to modern phraseology and notation. These will accordingly 
be employed, as usual, when we come to the actual propositions of the treatise. 

72 



100 ARCHIMEDES 

return to the position from which it started, the figure compre- 
hended by the section of the right-angled cone is called a right- 
angled conoid, and the diameter which has remained fixed 
is called its axis, while its vertex is the point in which the 
axis meets (airrerai) the surface of the conoid. And if a plane 
touch the right-angled conoid, and another plane drawn parallel 
to the tangent plane cut off a segment of the conoid, the base 
of the segment cut off is defined as the portion intercepted by 
the section of the conoid on the cutting plane, the vertex 
[of the segment] as the point in which the first plane touches 
the conoid, and the axis [of the segment] as the portion cut 
off within the segment from the line drawn through the vertex 
of the segment parallel to the axis of the conoid. 

The questions propounded for consideration were 

(1) why, if a segment of the right-angled conoid be cut off 
by a plane at right angles to the axis, will the segment so cut 
off be half as large again as the cone which has the same base 
as the segment and the same axis, and 

(2) why, if two segments be cut off from the right-angled 
conoid by planes drawn in any manner, will the segments so cut 
off have to one another the duplicate ratio of their axes. 

II. Respecting the obtuse-angled conoid we lay down the 
following premisses. If there be in a plane a section of an 
obtuse-angled cone [a hyperbola], its diameter [axis], and the 
nearest lines to the section of the obtuse-angled cone [i.e. the 
asymptotes of the hyperbola], and if, the diameter [axis] 
remaining fixed, the plane containing the aforesaid lines be 
made to revolve about it and return to the position from which 
it started, the nearest lines to the section of the obtuse-angled 
cone [the asymptotes] will clearly comprehend an isosceles cone 
whose vertex will be the point of concourse of the nearest lines 
and whose axis will be the diameter [axis] which has remained 
fixed. The figure comprehended by the section of the obtuse- 
angled cone is called an obtuse-angled conoid [hyperboloid of 
revolution], its axis is the diameter which has remained fixed, 
and its vertex the point in which the axis meets the surface 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 101 

of the conoid. The cone comprehended by the nearest lines to 
the section of the obtuse-angled cone is called [the cone] 
enveloping the conoid (irepiexcov TO fcwvoeiSes), and the 
straight line between the vertex of the conoid and the vertex 
of the cone enveloping the conoid is called [the line] adjacent 
to the axis (iroTeovtra rc5 agovi). And if a plane touch the 
obtuse-angled conoid, and another plane drawn parallel to the 
tangent plane cut off a segment of the conoid, the base of 
the segment so cut off is defined as the portion intercepted by 
the section of the conoid on the cutting plane, the vertex [of 
the segment] as the point of contact of the plane which touches 
the conoid, the axis [of the segment] as the portion cut off 
within the segment from the line drawn through the vertex of 
the segment and the vertex of the cone enveloping the conoid ; 
and the straight line between the said vertices is called 
adjacent to the axis. 

Right-angled conoids are all similar; but of obtuse-angled 
conoids let those be called similar in which the cones enveloping 
the conoids are similar. 

The following questions are propounded for consideration, 

(1) why, if a segment be cut off from the obtuse-angled 
conoid by a plane at right angles to the axis, the segment so 
cut off has to the cone which has the same base as the segment 
and the same axis the ratio which the line equal to the sum 
of the axis of the segment and three times the line adjacent 
to the axis bears to the line equal to the sum of the axis of 
the segment and twice the line adjacent to the axis, and 

(2) why, if a segment of the obtuse-angled conoid be cut 
off by a plane not at right angles to the axis, the segment so 
cut off will bear to the figure which has the same base as 
the segment and the same axis, being a segment of a cone* 
(atrorp.afjLa tcwvov), the ratio which the line equal to the sum 
of the axis of the segment and three times the line adjacent 
to the axis bears to the line equal to the sum of the axis of the 
segment and twice the line adjacent to the axis. 

* A segment of a cone is defined later (p. 104). 



102 ARCHIMEDES 

III. Concerning spheroidal figures we lay down the follow- 
ing premisses. If a section of an acute-angled cone [ellipse] be 
made to revolve about the greater diameter [major axis] which 
remains fixed and return to the position from which it started, 
the figure comprehended by the section of the acute-angled 
cone is called an oblong spheroid (trapap.aK^ <r<<upoei8e?). 
But if the section of the acute-angled cone revolve about the 
lesser diameter [minor axis] which remains fixed and return 
to the position from which it started, the figure comprehended 
by the section of the acute-angled cone is called a flat spheroid 
(eTTiTrXarv ffQaipoeiSes). In either of the spheroids the axis 
is defined as the diameter [axis] which has remained fixed, the 
vertex as the point in which the axis meets the surface of the 
spheroid, the centre as the middle point of the axis, and the 
diameter as the line drawn through the centre at right angles 
to the axis. And, if parallel planes touch, without cutting, 
either of the spheroidal figures, and if another plane be drawn 
parallel to the tangent planes and cutting the spheroid, the 
base of the resulting segments is defined as the portion inter- 
cepted by the section of the spheroid on the cutting plane, their 
vertices as the points in which the parallel planes touch the 
spheroid, and their axes as the portions cut off within the 
segments from the straight line joining their vertices. And 
that the planes touching the spheroid meet its surface at one 
point only, and that the straight line joining the points of 
contact passes through the centre of the spheroid, we shall 
prove. Those spheroidal figures are called similar in which 
the axes have the same ratio to the 'diameters/ And let 
segments of spheroidal figures and conoids be called similar if 
they are cut off from similar figures and have their bases 
similar, while their axes, being either at right angles to the 
planes of the bases or making equal angles with the corre- 
sponding diameters [axes] of the bases, have the same ratio 
to one another as the corresponding diameters [axes] of the 



The following questions about spheroids are propounded for 
consideration, 

(1) why, if one of the spheroidal figures be cut by a plane 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 103 

through the centre at right angles to the axis, each of the 
resulting segments will be double of the cone having the same 
base as the segment and the same axis ; while, if the plane of 
section be at right angles to the axis without passing through 
the centre, (a) the greater of the resulting segments will bear 
to the cone which has the same base as the segment and the 
same axis the ratio which the line equal to the sum of half the 
straight line which is the axis of the spheroid and the axis of 
the lesser segment bears to the axis of the lesser segment, and 
(6) the lesser segment bears to the cone which has the same 
base as the segment and the same axis the ratio which the line 
equal to the sum of half the straight line which is the axis 
of the spheroid and the axis of the greater segment bears to the 
axis of the greater segment ; 

(2) why, if one of the spheroids be cut by a plane passing 
through the centre but not at right angles to the axis, each of 
the resulting segments will be double of the figure having the 
same base as the segment and the same axis and consisting of a 
segment of a cone*. 

(3) But, if the plane cutting the spheroid be neither 
through the centre nor at right angles to the axis, (a) the 
greater of the resulting segments will have to the figure 
which has the same base as the segment and the same axis 
the ratio which the line equal to the sum of half the line 
joining the vertices of the segments and the axis of the lesser 
segment bears to the axis of the lesser segment, and (6) the 
lesser segment will have to the figure with the same base 
as the segment and the same axis the ratio which the line 
equal to the sum of half the line joining the vertices of the 
segments and the axis of the greater segment bears to the axis 
of the greater segment. And the figure referred to is in these 
cases also a segment of a cone*. 

When the aforesaid theorems are proved, there are dis- 
covered by means of them many theorems and problems. 
Such, for example, are the theorems 
(1) that similar spheroids and similar segments both of 

* See the definition of a segment of a cone (MrnafM K&*OV) on p. 104. 



104 ARCHIMEDES 

spheroidal figures and conoids have to one another the triplicate 
ratio of their axes, and 

(2) that in equal spheroidal figures the squares on the 
' diameters ' are reciprocally proportional to the axes, and, if in 
spheroidal figures the squares on the ' diameters 1 are reciprocally 
proportional to the axes, the spheroids are equal. 

Such also is the problem, From a given spheroidal figure 
or conoid to cut off a segment by a plane drawn parallel to a 
given plane so that the segment cut off is equal to a given cone 
or cylinder or to a given sphere. 

After prefixing therefore the theorems and directions (eVi- 
Tayiuvra) which are necessary for the proof of them, I will 
then proceed to expound the propositions themselves to you. 
Farewell. 

DEFINITIONS. 

If a cone be cut by a plane meeting all the sides [generators] 
of the cone, the section will be either a circle or a section of an 
acute-angled cone [an ellipse]. If then the section be a circle, 
it is clear that the segment cut off from the cone towards the 
same parts as the vertex of the cone will be a cone. But, if 
the section be a section of an acute-angled cone [an ellipse], let 
the figure cut off from the cone towards the same parts as the 
vertex of the cone be called a segment of a cone. Let the 
base of the segment be defined as the plane comprehended by 
the section of the acute-angled cone, its vertex as the point 
which is also the vertex of the cone, and its aads as the straight 
line joining the vertex of the cone to the centre of the section 
of the acute-angled cone. 

And if a cylinder be cut by two parallel planes meeting all 
the sides [generators] of the cylinder, the sections will be either 
circles or sections of acute-angled cones [ellipses] equal and 
similar to one another. If then the sections be circles, it is 
clear that the figure cut off from the cylinder between the 
parallel planes will be a cylinder. But, if the sections be 
sections of acute-angled cones [ellipses], let the figure cut off 
from the cylinder between the parallel planes be called a 
frustum (TO/UO?) of a cylinder. And let the bases of the 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 105 

frustum be defined as the planes comprehended by the sections 
of the acute-angled cones [ellipses], and the axis as the straight 
line joining the centres of the sections of the acute-angled 
cones, so that the axis will be in the same straight line with 
the axis of the cylinder." 

Lemma. 

If in an ascending arithmetical progression consisting of the 
magnitudes A Jt A^, ... A n the common difference be equal to the 
least term A lt then 



and 

[The proof of this is given incidentally in the treatise On 
Spirals, Prop. 11. By placing lines side by side to represent 
the terms of the progression and then producing each so as to 
make it equal to the greatest term, Archimedes gives the 
equivalent of the following proof. 

If Sn^Ai+Ai+.^+A^ + An, 

we have also S n = A n + A n ^ + A n ^ + ...4- -4,. 

And A l + -4 n _j = A 2 + A n ^ 2 = ... = A n . 

Therefore 2S n = (n + 1) A nt 

whence n . A n < 2S nt 

and n.A n >2S n - l . 

Thus, if the progression is a, 2a, . . . na, 



a, 



and /i*a<2S n , 

but >2S IM .] 

Proposition 1. 

If A lf B lt C l9 .../fj and A^, jB 2 , (7 3 , ...K^ be two series of 
magnitudes such that 

A , D __ A . JJ \ 

/Ij . JDj = -/Ij x^ji I 

J?, : C^ss-Bj : (7,, a?id so on j ^ ' 



106 ARCHIMEDES 

and if A 3 , B 3 , d> ...K z and A 4 , B 4 , d, ...K 4 be two other series 
such that 

A\ I A$ = ^1 2 : -"-4* 

B l :B S =B Z :B 4 , and soon 
then ( 



1 /g\ 

) .............. ^ P '' 



The proof is as follows. 

Since A 3 : A l = A 4 : A.,, 

and A l :B l ^A 9 :B. 9 

while Bi-.Bi^Bt-.Bt, 

we have, ex aequali, A 3 : B 3 = A 4 : B 4 . \ 

Similarly B 3 :C 3 =B^:C 4t and so on j 

Again, it follows from equations (a) that 



Therefore 

A, : A,^(A, + B t + d + ... + /TO : (A 9 +B 9 -h ... + 
or (A + B l + d + -.. + #0 : ^i = (A, + B 2 + C..+ ... + 
and A l :A 3 = A: A^ 

while from equations (7) it follows in like manner that 



By the last three equations, ex aequali, 



COR. If any terms in the third and fourth series corre- 
sponding to terms in the first and second be left out, the 
result is the same. For example, if the last terms K 3 , K 4 are 
absent, 



where I immediately precedes K in each series. 



OK CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



107 



Lemma to Proposition 2. 

[On Spirals, Prop. 10.] 

// A 19 A*> A 3t ...A n be n lines forming an ascending 
arithmetical progression in which the common difference is equal 
to the least term A lt then 



(n 



A l (A l 



Ai A 2 



n- 3 A-2A n _, 



AH Aft_i A..,j AB Aj AI 

Let the lines A n , A n - lt -4 n _ 2 , ...A l be placed in a row 
from left to right. Produce A n - lt A n _, ...Ai until they are 
each equal to A ni so that the parts produced are respectively 
equal to A l9 A. 2 , ...4 n _,. 

Taking each line successively, we have 



(A, + A n _tf = A? + 

\A Z 4* -"-n a) == A^ 4* < 



"t" ^^2' "n a 



108 ARCHIMEDES 

And, by addition, 



+ 24, . An-i + 24 2 . 4 n _ 2 4- . . . + 24^ . 4, . 

Therefore, in order to obtain the required result, we have to 
prove that 



+ ... + A n * ............ (a). 

Now 24 3 . 4 n _ 2 as A l . 44 n _ 2 , because 4 2 = 24i , 
24 8 . A n -t = A l . 6 4 n _ s , because A s = 34j , 



It follows that 



And this last expression can be proved to be equal to 

A* + A*+... + A n *. 

For An^A^n.An) 



because (n 1) A n = -4 n _, 4- 

4- -"-n 2 4- 
f 



Similarly 4 Vi = ^! {^n^ -f 2(4 7l _ 2 -f 4 n _ 8 4- 



whence, by addition, 

A n t 

1 + 5A n - t + ... +(2n- 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 109 

Thus the equation marked (a) above is true ; and it follows 
that 



. 

COR. 1. From this it is evident that 

n.A n ><3(A' + A*+...+A n *) ............. (1). 

Also An^A^An + ^A^ + An-i+.-.+At)}, as above, 
so that An > A^An + A n ^ + ... -Mi), 
and therefore 



It follows from the proposition that 

_ 1 ) .................. (2). 



COR. 2. All these results will hold if we substitute similar 
figures for squares on all the lines ; for similar figures are in the 
duplicate ratio of their sides. 

[In the above proposition the symbols A lt A^, ...A n have 
been used instead of a, 2a, 3a, ...na in order to exhibit the 
geometrical character of the proof ; but, if we now substitute 
the latter terms in the various results, we have (1) 

(n + 1) nV + a(a + 2a + ... 4- na) 

= 3 {a 2 4- (2a) 2 + (3a)* + . . . + (a) f j. 

Therefore a 9 + (2a) a + (3a) 2 + . . . + (na) 2 

n ( n + !)} 

a } 



a * (/ , -i \ 

8l ( " +1) " 



_. _ 

Also(2) i' 
and (3) n' 



110 ARCHIMEDES 

Proposition 3. 

IfA lt A 2 ... A n be any number of areas such that* 
A l = 00 + s , 



A n a. nx + (nx)* y 

(* )~iff\ 
2 + T j ' 

(ft 7i^?*\ 
S + -Q- 
L O / 

For, by the Lemma immediately preceding Prop. 1, 

n . anx < 2 (ax + a . 20 + . . . + a . nx) y 
and > 2 (ax + a . 20 + . . . + a . /T^T #). 

Also, by the Lemma preceding this proposition, 
n . (nx)* < 3 {x* + (2#)' + (30)" + . . . + (/w?)"} 
and > 3 {0 2 + (20) 1 + . . . + (n~^~T a;) 2 }. 

Hence 

ClfflQC VL ( fUE I 

-y + -y- ; - < [(00 4- 0>) + {a . 20 -f (20/J + . . . + {a . n0 ^(710)") 
and 
> [(00 + s ) + {a . 2# -t- (2#) 2 j + ... + {a . ti^l x -f (?i-"l 0) 1 }], 



an*x 



and 

It follows that 



or n.A n :(A l 

also n.^ n :(^ 1 

* The phraseology of Archimedes here is that associated with the traditional 
method of application of areas: rf K a...irap Ard^ra* atrav wapairfov n xupiov 
vvtppd\\ov cfdci TTpay6vt? t if to each of the lines there be applied a space 
[rectangle] exceeding by a square figure. " Thus A l is a rectangle of height x ap- 
plied to a line a but overlapping it so that the base extends a distance x beyond a. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



Ill 



Proposition 3. 

(1) If TP, TP' be two tangents to any conic meeting in T, 
and if Qq, Q'q' be any two chords parallel respectively to TP, 
TP' and meeting in 0, then 

QO.Oq:Q'O.Oq'=TP*: TP". 
" And this is proved in the elements of conies*." 

(2) If QQ' be a chord of a parabola bisected in V by the 
diameter PV, and if PV be of constant length, then the areas of 
the triangle PQQ' and of the segment PQQ' are both constant 
whatever be the direction of QQ'. 

Let ABB' be the particular segment of the parabola whose 
vertex is A, so that BE' is bisected perpendicularly by the axis 
at the point H, where AH = PV. 

Draw QD perpendicular to PV. 




Let p a be the parameter of the principal ordinates, and let 
p be another line of such length that 

QV-.QD'-p-.p.; 

it will then follow that p is equal to the parameter of the ordi- 
nates to the diameter PV, i.e. those which are parallel to QV. 

* i.e. in the treatises on conies by Aristaeus and Euclid. 



112 ARCHIMEDES 

" For this is proved in the conies*." 

Thus QV*=p.PV. 

And BH*=p a .AH, while AH=PV. 
Therefore QF 1 : BH* = p:p a . 

But QV*:QD*=p:p a ; 

hence BH = QD. 

Thus BH.AH=QD.PV, 

and therefore A 4 JBJ3' = A PQQ' ; 

that is, the area of the triangle PQQ' is constant so long as PV 
is of constant length. 

Hence also the area of the segment PQQ' is constant under 
the same conditions; for the segment is equal to $APQQ'. 
[Quadrature of the Parabola, Prop. 17 or 24.] 

* The theorem which is here assumed by Archimedes as known can be 
proved in various ways. 

(1) It is easily deduced from Apollonius I. 49 (cf. Apollonius of Perga, 
pp. liii, 39). If in the figure the tangents at A and P be drawn, the former 
meeting PV in E, and the latter meeting the axis in T, and if AE, PT meet 
at C, the proposition of Apollonius is to the effect that 



where p is the parameter of the ordinates to PV. 

(2) It may be proved independently as follows. 

Let QQ' meet the axis in O, and let QM, Q'JT, PN be ordinates to the axis. 

Then AM : A M' = QM* : Q'M'* = OM* : < 

whence AM : MM'= OJf : OJ/ 2 - O J/ 

= OJ/ 3 :(OJ/-OJ/')., 
BO that OJf *=AM . (OJ/- OM'). 

That is to say, (AM- AO)*=AM .(AM+AM' -2AO), 
or AO*=AM.AM'. 

And, since QM*=p a .AM, and Q'M'* = p a .AM f , 
it follows that QM .Q'M' = p a .AO (a). 

Now QV* : QD*=QV* : (Q M + Q' M '\ 2 



= QV*:(PN*+QM.Q'M') 
=p.PV:p a .(AN+AO),l)y(a). 

But PV=TO=AN+AO. 

Therefore QV* : QD * = p : p a . 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



113 



Proposition 4. 

The area of any ellipse is to that of the auxiliary circle as 
the minor axis to the major. 

Let AA' be the major and BB' the minor axis of the 
ellipse, and let BB' meet the auxiliary circle in 6, b'. 

Suppose to be such a circle that 

(circle AbA'V) :0 = CA:CB. 
Then shall be equal to the area of the ellipse. 

For, if not, must be either greater or less than the 
ellipse. 

I. If possible, let be greater than the ellipse. 

We can then inscribe in the circle an equilateral polygon 
of 4w sides such that its area is greater than that of the ellipse, 
[cf. OH the Sphere and Cylinder, I. 0.] 




Let this be done, and inscribe in the auxiliary circle of the 
ellipse the polygon AefbghA'... similar to that inscribed in 0. 
Let the perpendiculars eM, /JV,... on AA' meet the ellipse in 
E, F,. . . respectively. Join A E t EF, FB,. . .. 

Suppose that P' denotes the area of the polygon inscribed 
in the auxiliary circle, and P that of the polygon inscribed in 
the ellipse. 



H. A. 



8 



114 ARCHIMEDES 

Then, since all the lines eM, fN,. . . are cut in the same 
proportions at E y F,... f 

i.e. eM : EM=fN :FN=... = bC : BC, 

the paii*s of triangles, as eAM 9 EAM, and the pairs of trapeziums, 
as eMNf, EMNF, are all in the same ratio to one another 
as bC to BC, or as CA to CB. 

Therefore, by addition, 

P':P = CA:CB. 

Now P' : (polygon inscribed in 0) 

= (circle AbA 'V) : () 

= CA : CB, by hypothesis. 

Therefore P is equal to the polygon inscribed in 0. 

But this is impossible, because the latter polygon is by 
hypothesis greater than the ellipse, and a fortiori greater 
than P. 

Hence is not greater than the ellipse. 

II. If possible, let be less than the ellipse. 

In this case we inscribe in the ellipse a polygon P with In 
equal sides such that P > 0. 

Let the perpendiculars from the angular points on the 
axis AA' be produced to meet the auxiliary circle, and let the 
corresponding polygon (P f ) in the circle be formed. 

Inscribe in a polygon similar to P'. 

Then P':P = CA:CB 

= (circle AbA'b') : 0, by hypothesis, 
= P' : (polygon inscribed in O). 

Therefore the polygon inscribed in is equal to the 
polygon P ; which is impossible, because P > 0. 

Hence 0, being neither greater nor less than the ellipse, is 
equal to it ; and the required result follows. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 115 



Proposition 5. 

If AA', BE' be the major and minor axis of an ellipse 
respectively, and if d be the diameter of any circle, then 

(area of ellipse) : (area of circle) = A A' . BE' : d' 2 . 
For 
(area of ellipse) : (area of auxiliary circle) = BE' : A A [Prop. 4] 

= AA'.BB': A A". 
And 

(area of aux. circle) : (area of circle with diam. d) = A A* : tf. 
Therefore the required result follows ex aequali 

Proposition 6. 

The areas of ellipses are as the rectangles under their axes. 
This follows at once from Props. 4, 5. 

COR. The areas of similar ellipses are as the squares of 
corresponding a.i-es. 

Proposition 7. 

Given an ellipse with centre C, and a line CO drawn per- 
pendicular to its plane, it is possible to find a circular cone 
with vertex and such that the given ellipse is a section of it 
[or, in other words, to find ilie circular sections of the cone with 
vertex passing through the circumference of the ellipse]. 

Conceive an ellipse with BB' as its minor axis and lying in 
a plane perpendicular to that of the paper. Let CO be drawn 
perpendicular to the plane of the ellipse, and let be the 
vertex of the required cone. Produce OB, 00, OB' t and in the 
.same plane with them draw BED meeting 0(7, OB' produced 
in E, D respectively and in such a direction that 

BE. ED : EO* = CA* : C0\ 
where CA is half the major axis of the ellipse. 

82 



116 



ARCHIMEDES 



" And this is possible, since 

BE. ED: EO* > BC. CB' : CO*" 

[Both the construction and this proposition are assumed as 
known.] 




Now conceive a circle with BD as diameter lying in a plane 
at right angles to that of the paper, and describe a cone with 
this circle for its base and with vertex 0. 

We have therefore to prove that the given ellipse is a 
section of the cone, or, if P be any point on the ellipse, that P 
lies on the surface of the cone. 

Draw PN perpendicular to BK'. Join ON and produce it 
to meet BD in M t and let MQ be drawn in the plane of the 
circle on BD as diameter perpendicular to BD and meeting the 
circle in Q. Also let FG, HK be drawn through E, M respec- 
tively parallel to BB'. 

We have then 



= BE.ED:FE.EG 
= (BE. ED : EO*) . (EO 9 : FE.EG) 
= (CA*:CO*).(CO*:BC.CB') 
= CA* : CB* 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 117 

Therefore QM> : PN* = HM.MK:BN. NB' 



whence, since PN, QM are parallel, OPQ is a straight line. 

But Q is on the circumference of the circle on BD as 
diameter ; therefore OQ is a generator of the cone, and hence 
P lies on the cone. 

Thus the cone passes through all points on the ellipse. 

Proposition 8. 

Given an ellipse, a plane through one of its axes A A' and 
perpendicular to the plane of the ellipse, and a line CO drawn 
from C, the centre, in the given plane through AA' but not 
perpendicular to AA e , it is possible to find a cone with vertex 
such that the given ellipse is a section of it [or, in other words, 
to find the circular sections of the cone with vertex whose 
surface passes through the circumference of the ellipse]. 

By hypothesis, OA, OA' are unequal. Produce QA' to D so 
that OA = OD. Join A D, and draw FG through C parallel to it. 

The given ellipse is to be supposed to lie in a plane per- 
pendicular to the plane of the paper. Let BB' be the other 
axis of the ellipse. 

Conceive a plane through AD perpendicular to the plane 
of the paper, and in it describe either (a), if CB* = FC. CG, a 
circle with diameter AD, or (b\ if not, an ellipse on AD as 
axis such that, if d be the other axis, 



Take a cone with vertex whose surface passes through 
the circle or ellipse just drawn. This is possible even when the 
curve is an ellipse, because the line from to the middle point 
of AD is perpendicular to the plane of the ellipse, and the 
construction is effected by means of Prop. 7. 

Let P be any point on the given ellipse, and we have only 
to prove that P lies on the surface of the cone so described 



118 ARCHIMEDES 

Draw PN perpendicular to AA'. Join ON, and produce it 
to meet AD in M. Through M draw HK parallel to A' A. 




Lastly, draw MQ perpendicular to the plane of the paper 
(and therefore perpendicular to both HK and AD) meeting the 
ellipse or circle about AD (and therefore the surface of the cone) 
in Q. 
Then 

QM* : HM . MK - (QM 9 : DM . MA ) . (DM . MA : HM . MK) 
= (d 2 : AD*).(FC. GG : A'C. CA) 
= (Ctf* : FC . CG).(FC.CG : AC .CA) 
= CB* : CA* 
= PN*:A'N.NA. 
Therefore, alternately, 

QM : PN* - HM. MK : A' XT . NA 

= OM* : ON*. 

Thus, since PN, QM are parallel, OPQ is a straight line ; 
and, Q being on the surface of the cone, it follows that P is also 
on the surface of the cone. 

Similarly all points on the ellipse are also on the cone, and 
the ellipse is therefore a section of the cone. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 119 

Proposition 9. 

Given an ellipse, a plane through one of its axes and perpen- 
dicular to that of the ellipse, and a straight line CO drawn from 
the centre of the ellipse in the given plane through the axis but 
not perpendicular to that axis, it is possible to find a cylinder 
with axis OC such that the ellipse is a section of it [or, in other 
words, to find the circular sections of the cylinder with axis OC 
whose surface passes through the circumference of the given 
ellipse]. 

Let A A' be an axis of the ellipse, and suppose the plane 
of the ellipse to be perpendicular to that of the paper, so that 
OC lies in the plane of the paper. 




Draw AD, A'E parallel to CO, and let DE be the line 
through perpendicular to both AD and A'E. 

We have now three different cases according as the other 
axis BW of the ellipse is (1) equal to, (2) greater than, or 
(3) less than, DE. 

(1) Suppose BB' = DE. 

Draw a plane through DE at right angles to OC, and in 
this plane describe a circle on DE as diameter. Through this 
circle describe a cylinder with axis OC. 

This cylinder shall be the cylinder required, or its surface 
shall pass through every point P of the ellipse. 

For, if P be any point on the ellipse, draw PN perpendicular 
to A A' ; through N draw NM parallel to CO meeting DE in 
M, and through Af, in the plane of the circle on DE as diameter, 
draw MQ perpendicular to DE, meeting the circle in Q. 



120 



ARCHIMEDES 



Then, since DE = BB', 

PN* : AN,NA' = DO' : A C. CA. 



And 
since AD, NM, CO, A'E are parallel. 

Therefore PN* = DM.ME 

= QM>, 
by the property of the circle. 

Hence, since PN, QM are equal as well as parallel, PQ is 
parallel to MN and therefore to CO. It follows that PQ is a 
generator of the cylinder, whose surface accordingly passes 
through P. 

(2) If BB' > DE y we take E' on A'E such that DE' = BB' 
and describe a circle on DE' as diameter in a plane perpen- 
dicular to that of the paper ; and the rest of the construction 
and proof is exactly similar to those given for case (1). 

(3) Suppose BB' < DE. 

Take a point K on CO produced such that 



From K draw KR perpendicular to the plane of the paper 
and equal to CB. 

Thus OR 9 OK 9 + CB 9 = OD*. 




In the plane containing DE, OR describe a circle on DE an 
diameter. Through this circle (which must pass through R) 
draw a cylinder with axis OC. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 121 

We have then to prove that, if P be any point on the given 
ellipse, P lies on the cylinder so described. 

Draw PN perpendicular to AA', and through N draw NM 
parallel to CO meeting DE in M. In the plane of the circle on 
DE as diameter draw MQ perpendicular to DE and meeting 
the circle in Q. 

Lastly, draw QH perpendicular to NM produced. QH will 
then be perpendicular to the plane containing AC, DE t i.e. the 
plane of the paper. 

Now QH 2 : QM* = KR* : OR\ by similar triangles. 

And QM 2 : AN. NA' = DM. ME : AN. NA' 

= OZ> 2 : CA\ 
Hence, ex aequali, since OR = OD, 

QH*:AN.NA' = KR*:CA* 
- CB* : CA* 
= PN*:AN.NA'. 

Thus QH = PN. And QH, PN are also parallel. Accordingly 
PQ is parallel to MN, and therefore to CO, so that PQ is a 
generator, and the cylinder passes through P. 

Proposition 1O. 

It was proved by the earlier geometers that any two cones 
have to one another the ratio compounded of the ratios of their 
bases and of their heights*. The same method of proof will 
show that any segments of cones have to one another the ratio 
compounded of the ratios of their bases and of their heights. 

The proposition that any 'frustum ' of a cylinder is triple 
of the conical segment which has the same base as the frustum 
and equal height is also proved in the same manner as the 
proposition that the cylinder is triple of the cone which has 
the same base as the cylinder and equal height^. 

* This follows from Eucl. xu. 11 and 14 taken together. Cf. On the Sphere 
and Cylinder i, Lemma 1. 

t This proposition was proved by Eudoxus, as stated in the preface to On 
the Sphere and Cylinder i. Cf. Eucl. xu. 10. 



122 ARCHIMEDES 

Proposition 11. 

(1) If a paraboloid of revolution be cut by a plane through, 
or parallel to, the axis, the section will be a parabola equal to the 
original parabola which by its revolution generates the paraboloid. 
And the axis of the section urill be the intersection between the 
cutting plane and the plane through the axis of the paraboloid 
at right angles to the cutting plane. 

If the paraboloid be cut by a plane at right angles to its 
axis, the section will be a circle whose centre is on the axis. 

(2) If a hyperboloid of revolution be cut by a plane through 
the axis, parallel to the axis, or through the centre, the section 
will be a hyperbola, (a) if the section be through the axis, equal, 
(b) if parallel to the axis, similar, (c) if through the centre, 
not similar, to the original hyperbola which by its revolution 
generates the hyperboloid. And the axi.s of the section will be 
the intersection of the cutting plane and the plane through the 
axis of the hyperboloid at right angles to the cutting plane. 

Any section of the hyperboloid by a plane at right angles to 
the axis will be a circle whose centre is on the axis. 

(3) If any of the spheroidal figures be cut by a plane through 
the axis or parallel to the axis, the section will be an ellipse, 
(a) if the section be through the axis, equal, (b) if parallel to the 
axis, similar, to the ellipse which by its revolution generates the 
figure. And the axis of the section will be ike intersection of the 
cutting plane and the plane through the axis of the spheroid 
at right angles to the cutting plane. 

If the section be by a plane at right angles to the axis of the 
sph^oid, it will be a circle whose centre is on the axis. 

(4) If any of the said figures be cut by a plane through the 
axis, and if a perpendicular be drawn to the plane of section 
from any point on the surface of the figure but not on the section, 
that perpendicular will fall within the section. 

" And the proofs of all these propositions are evident."* 
* Cf. the Introduction, chapter HI. 4. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



123 



Proposition 12. 

If a paraboloid of revolution be cut by a plane neither parallel 
nor perpendicular to the axis, and if the plane through the axis 
perpendicukir to the cutting plane intersect it in a straight line 
of which the portion intercepted within the paraboloid is RR, 
the section of the paraboloid ivill be an ellipse whose major axis 
is RR' and whose minor axis is equal to the perpendicular 
distance between the lines through R, R parallel to the axis 
of the paraboloid. 

Suppose the cutting plane to be perpendicular to the plane 
of the paper, and let the latter be the plane through the axis 
ANF of the paraboloid which intersects the cutting plane at 
right angles in RR. Let RH be parallel to the axis of the 
paraboloid, and R'H perpendicular to RH. 

Let Q be any point on the section made by the cutting 
plane, and from Q draw QM perpendicular to RR. QM will 
therefore be perpendicular to the plane of the paper. 

Through M draw DMFE perpendicular to the axis ANF 
meeting the parabolic section made by the plane of the paper 
in D, E. Then QM is perpendicular to DE, and, if a plane be 
drawn through DE, QM, it will be perpendicular to the axis 
and will cut the paraboloid in a circular section. 




Since Q is on this circle, 



Again, if PT be that tangent to the parabolic section in the 



124 



ARCHIMEDES 



plane of the paper which is parallel to RR', and if the tangent 
at A meet PT in 0, then, from the property of the parabola, 

DM.ME:RM.MR' = AO*:OP* [Prop. 3 (1)] 

= AO* : 02", since AN** AT. 

Therefore QM* : RM . MR' A O 2 : 



by similar triangles. 

Hence Q lies on an ellipse whose major axis is RR' and 
whose minor axis is equal to R'H. 



Propositions 13, 14. 

If a hyperboloid of revolution be cut by a plane meeting all 
the generators of the enveloping cone, or if an ' oblong ' spheroid 
be cut by a plane not perpendicular to the axis*, and if a plane 
through the axis intersect the cutting plane at right angles in a 
straight line on which the hyperboloid or spheroid intercepts 
a length RR', then the section by the cutting plane will be an 
ellipse whose major axis is RR'. 

Suppose the cutting plane to be at right angles to the 
plane of the paper, and suppose the latter plane to be that 




* Archimedes begins Prop. 14 for the spheroid with the remark that, when the 
catting plane passes through or is parallel to the axis, the case is clear (^Aov). 
Cf. Prop. 11 (3). 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 125 

through the axis ANF which intersects the cutting plane 
at right angles in RR'. The section of the hyperboloid or 
spheroid by the plane of the paper is thus a hyperbola or ellipse 
having ANF for its transverse or major axis. 

Take any point on the section made by the cutting plane, 
as Q, and draw QM perpendicular to RR'. QM will then 
be perpendicular to the plane of the paper. 

Through M draw DFE at right angles to the axis ANF 
meeting the hyperbola or ellipse in D, E\ and through QM, 
DE let a plane be described. This plane will accordingly be 
perpendicular to the axis and will cut the hyperboloid or 
spheroid in a circular section. 

Thus QM* = DM.ME. 

Let PT be that tangent to the hyperbola or ellipse which 
is parallel to RR', and let the tangent at A meet PT in 0. 

Then, by the property of the hyperbola or ellipse, 

DM. ME : RM.MR' = OA* : OP 2 , 
or QM* : RM. MR = OA* : OP 2 . 

Now (1) in the hyperbola OA < OP, because AT< AN*, and 
accordingly OT < OP, while OA < OT y 

(2) in the ellipse, if KK' be the diameter parallel to RR', 
and BB f the minor axis, 

EG . CB' : KG . GK' = OA* : OP 2 ; 
and BC . CB' < KG . CK', so that OA < OP. 

Hence in both cases the locus of Q is an ellipse whose major 
axis is RR'. 

COR. 1. If the spheroid be a 'flat* spheroid, the section will 
be an ellipse, and everything will proceed as before except that 
RR' will in this case be the minor axis. 

CoR. 2. In all conoids or spheroids parallel sections will be 
similar, since the ratio OA* : OP* is the same for all the 
parallel sections. 

* With reference to this assumption of. the Introduction, chapter in. 3. 



126 ARCHIMEDES 

Proposition 15. 

(1) If from any point on the surface of a conoid a line be 
drawn, in the case of the paraboloid, parallel to the axis, and, in 
the case of the hyperboloid, parallel to any line passing through 
the vertex of the enveloping cone, the part of the straight line 
which is in the same direction as the convexity of the surface will 
fall without it, and the part which is in the oilier direction 
within it. 

For, if a plane be drawn, in the case of the paraboloid, 
through the axis and the point, and, in the case of the hyperbo- 
loid, through the given point and through the given straight 
line drawn through the vertex of the enveloping cone, the 
section by the plane will be (a) in the paraboloid a parabola 
whose axis is the axis of the paraboloid, (6) in the hyperboloid 
a hyperbola in which the given line through the vertex of the 
enveloping cone is a diameter*. [Prop. 11] 

Hence the property follows from the plane properties of the 
conies. 

(2) If a plane touch a conoid without cutting it, it will 
touch it at one point only, and the plane drawn through the 
point of contact and the axis of the conoid will be at right 
angles to the plane which touches it. 

For, if possible, let the plane touch at two points. Draw 
through each point a parallel to the axis. The plane passing 
through both parallels will therefore either pass through, or be 
parallel to, the axis. Hence the section of the conoid made by 
this plane will be a conic [Prop. 11 (1), (2)], the two points 
will lie on this conic, and the line joining them will lie within 
the conic and therefore within the conoid. But this line 
will be in the tangent plane, since the two points are in it. 
Therefore some portion of the tangent plane will be within 
the conoid; which is impossible, since the plane does not 
cut it. 

* There seems to be some error in the text here, which says that "the 
diameter" (i.e. axis) of the hyperbola is " the straight line drawn in the conoid 
from the vertex of the cone." But this straight line is not, in general, the 
axis of the section. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 127 

Therefore the tangent plane touches in one point only. 

That the plane through the point of contact and the axis is 
perpendicular to the tangent plane is evident in the particular 
case where the point of contact is the vertex of the conoid. 
For, if two planes through the axis cut it in two conies, the 
tangents at the vertex in both conies will be perpendicular 
to the axis of the conoid. And all such tangents will be in the 
tangent plane, which must therefore be perpendicular to the 
axis and to any plane through the axis. 

If the point of contact P is not the vertex, draw the plane 
passing through the axis AN and the point P. 
It will cut the conoid in a conic whose axis is 
AN and the tangent plane in a line DPE 
touching the conic at P. Draw PNP perpen- 
dicular to the axis, and draw a plane through it 
also perpendicular to the axis. This plane will 
make a circular section and meet the tangent 
plane in a tangent to the circle, which will 
therefore be at right angles to PN. Hence the 
tangent to the circle will be at right angles to the plane 
containing PN, AN\ and it follows that this last plane is 
perpendicular to the tangent plane. 

Proposition 16. 

( 1 ) If a plane touch any of the spheroidal figures without 
cutting it, it will touch at one point only, and the plane through 
the point of contact and the axis will be at right angles to the 
tangent plane. 

This is proved by the same method as the last proposition. 

(2) If any conoid or spheroid be cut by a plane through the 
axis, and if through any tangent to the resulting conic a plane be 
erected at right angles to the plane of section, the plane so erected 
will touch tlie conoid or spheroid in the same point as that in 
which the line touches the conic. 

For it cannot meet the surface at any other point. If it 
did, the perpendicular from the second point on the cutting 




128 ARCHIMEDES 

plane would be perpendicular also to the tangent to the conic 
and would therefore fall outside the surface. But it must fall 
within it. [Prop. 11 (4)] 

(3) If two parallel planes touch any of the splwoidal 
figures, the line joining the points of contact will pass through 
the centre of the sphwoid. 

If the planes are at right angles to the axis, the proposition 
is obvious. If not, the plane through the axis and one point of 
contact is at right angles to the tangent plane at that point. 
It is therefore at right angles to the parallel tangent plane, and 
therefore passes through the second point of contact. Hence 
both points of contact lie on one plane through the axis, and 
the proposition is reduced to a plane one. 

Proposition 17. 

If two parallel planes touch any of the spheroidal figures, 
and another plane be drawn parallel to the tangent planes and 
passing through the centre, the line drawn through any point of 
the circumference of the resulting section parallel to the chord 
of contact of the tangent planes will fall outside the spheroid. 

This is proved at once by reduction to a plane proposition. 

Archimedes adds that it is evident that, if the plane 
parallel to the tangent planes does not pass through the 
centre, a straight line drawn in the manner described will 
fall without the spheroid in the direction of the smaller 
segment but within it in the other direction. 

Proposition 18. 

Any spheroidal figure which is cut by a plane through the 
centre is divided, botfi as regards its surface and its volume, into 
two equal parts by that plane. 

To prove this, Archimedes takes another equal and similar 
spheroid, divides it similarly by a plane through the centre, and 
then uses the method of application. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 129 

Propositions 19, 2O. 

Given a segment cut off by a plane from a paraboloid or 
hyperboloid of revolution, or a segment of a spheroid less than 
half the spheroid also cut off by a plane, it is possible to inscribe 
in the segment one solid figure and to circumscribe about it 
another solid figure, each made up of cylinders or 'frusta ' of 
cylinders of equal height, and such that the circumscribed figure 
exceeds the inscribed figure by a volume less than that of any 
given solid. 

Let the plane base of the segment be perpendicular to the 
plane of the paper, and let the plane of the paper be the plane 
through the axis of the conoid or spheroid which cuts the base 
of the segment at right angles in BC. The section in the plane 
of the paper is then a conic BAG. [Prop. 11] 

Let EAF be that tangent to the conic which is parallel to 
BC, and let A be the point of contact. Through EAF draw 
a plane parallel to the plane through BC bounding the 
segment. The plane so drawn will then touch the conoid 
or spheroid at A. [Prop. 16] 

(1) If the base of the segment is at right angles to the 
axis of the conoid or spheroid, A will be the vertex of the 
conoid or spheroid, and its axis AD will bisect BC at right 
angles. 

(2) If the base of the segment is not at right angles to the 
axis of the conoid or spheroid, we draw AD 

(a) in the paraboloid, parallel to the axis, 

(b) in the hyperboloid, through the centre (or the vertex of 
the enveloping cone), 

(c) in the spheroid, through the centre, 

and in all the cases it will follow that AD bisects BC in D. 

Then A will be the vertex of the segment, and AD will be 
its axis. 

Further, the base of the segment will be a circle or an 
ellipse with BC as diameter or as an axis respectively, and 
with centre D. We can therefore describe through this circle 
H. A. 9 



130 ARCHIMEDES 

or ellipse a cylinder or a ' frustum ' of a cylinder whose axis is 
AD. * [Prop. 9] 




Dividing this cylinder or frustum continually into equal 
parts by planes parallel to the base, we shall at length arrive 
at a cylinder or frustum less in volume than any given solid. 

Let this cylinder or frustum be that whose axis is OD, and 
let AD be divided into parts equal to OD, at , J/,.... Through 
L, M 9 ... draw lines parallel to BC meeting the conic in P, (?,.> 
and through these lines draw planes parallel to the base of the 
segment. These will cut the conoid or spheroid in circles or 
similar ellipses. On each of these circles or ellipses describe 
two cylinders or frusta of cylinders each with axis equal to OD t 
one of them lying in the direction of A and the other in the 
direction of D, as shown in the figure. 

Then the cylinders or frusta of cylinders drawn in the 
Direction of A make up a circumscribed figure, and those in 
the direction of D an inscribed figure, in relation to the 
segment. 

Also the cylinder or frustum PG in the circumscribed figure 
is equal to the cylinder or frustum PH in the inscribed figure, 
QI in the circumscribed figure is equal to QK in the inscribed 
figure, and so on. 

Therefore, by addition, 
(circumscribed fig.) = (inscr. fig.) 

+ (cylinder or frustum whose axis is OD). 
But the cylinder or frustum whose axis is OD is less than 
the given solid figure ; whence the proposition follows. 



"Having set out these preliminary propositions, let us 
proceed to demonstrate the theorems propounded with reference 
to the figures." 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 131 

Propositions 21, 22. 

Any segment of a paraboloid of revolution is half as large 
again as the cone or segment of a cone which has the same base 
and the same axis. 

Let the base of the segment be perpendicular to the plane of 
the paper, and let the plane of the paper be the plane through 
the axis of the paraboloid which cuts the base of the segment 
at right angles in BO and makes the parabolic section BAG. 

Let EF be that tangent to the parabola which is parallel to 
BC, and let A be the point of contact. 

Then (I), if the plane of the base of the segment is 
perpendicular to the axis of the paraboloid, that axis is the 
line AD bisecting BC at right angles in D. 

(2) If the plane of the base is not perpendicular to the 
axis of the paraboloid, draw AD parallel to the axis of the 
paraboloid. AD will then bisect BC t but not at right angles. 

Draw through EF a plane parallel to the base of the seg- 
ment. This will touch the paraboloid at A, and A will be 
the vertex of the segment, AD its axis. 

The base of the segment will be a circle with diameter BC 
or an ellipse with BC as major axis. 

Accordingly a cylinder or a frustum of a cylinder can be 
found passing through the circle or ellipse and having AD for 
its axis [Prop. 9J ; and likewise a cone or a segment of a cone 
can be drawn passing through the circle or ellipse and having 
A for vertex and AD for axis. [Prop. 8] 

Suppose X to be a cone equal to f (cone or segment of 
cone ABC). The cone X is therefore equal to half the cylinder 
or frustum of a cylinder EC. [Cf. Prop. 10] 

We shall prove that the volume of the segment of the 
paraboloid is equal to X. 

If not, the segment must be either greater or less than X. 
I. If possible, let the segment be greater than X. 
We can then inscribe and circumscribe, as in the last 

92 



132 ARCHIMEDES 

proposition, figures made up of cylinders or frusta of cylinders 
with equal height and such that 

(circumscribed fig.) - (inscribed fig.) < (segment) - X. 

Let the greatest of the cylinders or frusta forming the 
circumscribed figure be that whose base is the circle or ellipse 
about BC and whose axis is OD, and let the smallest of them be 
that whose base is the circle or ellipse about PP' and whose 
axis is AL. 

Let the greatest of the cylinders forming the inscribed 
figure be that whose base is the circle or ellipse about RR' and 
whose axis is OJD, and let the smallest be that whose base is 
the circle or ellipse about PP' and whose axis is LM. 






L A/Q 



/ M 



/o 




Produce all the plane bases of the cylinders or frusta to 
meet the surface of the complete cylinder or frustum EC. 

Now, since 

(circumscribed fig.) (inscr. fig.) < (segment) X , 
it follows that (inscribed figure) > X (a). 

Next, comparing successively the cylinders or frusta with 
heights equal to OD and respectively forming parts of the 
complete cylinder or frustum EC and of the inscribed figure, 
we have 

(first cylinder or frustum in EC) : (first in inscr. fig.) 

= BD* : RO* 

=AD:AO 

= BD : TO, where AB meets OR in T. 
And (second cylinder or frustum in EC) : (second in inscr. fig.) 

= HO : SN, in like manner, 
and so on. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 133 

Hence [Prop. 1] (cylinder or frustum EC) : (inscribed figure) 

- (BD + HO+ ...) : (TO + SN+ ...), 

where BD, HO,... are all equal, and BD, TO, SN,... diminish in 
arithmetical progression. 

But [Lemma preceding Prop. 1] 

BD + HO + ... > 2(TO +SN+ ...). 

Therefore (cylinder or frustum EG) > 2 (inscribed fig.), 
or X > (inscribed fig.) ; 

which is impossible, by (a) above. 

II. If possible, let the segment be less than X. 
In this case we inscribe and circumscribe figures as before, 
but such that 

(circumscr. fig.) (inscr. fig.) < X - (segment), 
whence it follows that 

(circumscribed figure) < X ............... (ft). 

And, comparing the cylinders or frusta making up the 
complete cylinder or frustum GE and the circumscribed figure 
respectively, we have 

(first cylinder or frustum in CE) : (first in circumscr. fig.) 
= BD*:BD* 
= BD : BD. 
(second in CE) : (second in circumscr. fig.) 



=AD:AO 

= HO:TO, 
and so on. 

Hence [Prop. 1] 

(cylinder or frustum CE) : (circumscribed fig.) 



< 2 : 1, [Lemma preceding Prop. 1] 

and it follows that 

X < (circumscribed fig.) ; 

which is impossible, by (#). 

Thus the segment, being neither greater nor less than X, is 
equal to it, and therefore to f (cone or segment of cone ABO). 



134 



ARCHIMEDES 



Proposition 23. 

If from a paraboloid of revolution two segments be cut off, 
one by a plane perpendicular to the axis, the other by a plane not 
perpendicular to the axis, and if the axes of the segments are 
equal, the segments will be equal in volume. 

Let the two planes be supposed perpendicular to the plane 
of the paper, and let the latter plane be the plane through the 
axis of the paraboloid cutting the other two planes at right 
angles in BB f , QQ' respectively and the paraboloid itself in the 
parabola QPQ'B'. 

Let AN, PFbe the equal axes of the segments, and A, P 
their respective vertices. 




Draw QL parallel to AN or PV and Q'L perpendicular 
to QL. 

Now, since the segments of the parabolic section cut off by 
BB', QQ' have equal axes, the triangles ABB', PQQ f are equal 
[Prop. 3]. Also, if QD be perpendicular to PV, QD = BN (as 
in the same Prop. 3). 

Conceive two cones drawn with the same bases as the 
segments and with A, P as vertices respectively. The height 
of the cone PQQ' is then PK, where PK is perpendicular to 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



135 



Now the cones are in the ratio compounded of the ratios of 
their bases and of their heights, i.e. the ratio compounded of 
(1) the ratio of the circle about BB' to the ellipse about QQ', 
and (2) the ratio of AN to PK. 

That is to say, we have, by means of Props. 5, 12, 
(cone ABB') : (cone PQQ') = (BB' 9 : QQ' . Q'L) . (AN : PK). 
And BB' = 2BN = 2QD = Q'L, while QQ' = 2QV. 
Therefore 
(cone ABB') : (cone PQQ') = (QD:QV). (AN : PK) 

= (PK:PV).(AN:PK) 

= AN:PV. 

Since AN = PV t the ratio of the cones is a ratio of equality : 
and it follows that the segments, being each half as large again 
as the respective cones [Prop. 22], are equal. 

Proposition 24. 

If from a paraboloid of revolution two segments be cut off by 
planes draiun in any manner, the segments will be to one another 
as the squares on their axes. 

For let the paraboloid be cut by a plane through the axis 
in the parabolic section P'PApp, and let the axis of the 
parabola and paraboloid be ANN'. 

Measure along ANN' the lengths AN, AN' equal to the 
respective axes of the given segments, 
and through N, N' draw planes perpen- 
dicular to the axis, making circular 
sections on Pp, P'p' as diameters re- 
spectively. With these circles as bases 
and with the common vertex A let two 
cones be described. 

Now the segments of the paraboloid 
whose bases are the circles about Pp t 
P'f! are equal to the given segments 
respectively, since their respective axes 
are equal [Prop. 23]; and, since the 
segments APp, AP'p' are half as large 




136 ARCHIMEDES 

again as the cones APp, AP'p' respectively, we have only 
to show that the cones are in the ratio of A N* to AN'*. 

But 

(cone APp) : (cone APp') = (PN> : P'N'*).(AN : AN 1 ) 

= (AN: AN'). (AN: AN') 
= AN*: AN 19 ', 
thus the proposition is proved. 

Propositions 25, 26. 

In any hyperboloid of revolution, if A be the vertex and AD 
the axis of any segment cut off by a plane, and if CA be the 
semidiameter of the hyperboloid through A (CA being of course 
in the same straight line with AD), then 

(segment) : (cone with same base and axis) 

- (AD + ZCA) : (AD + 2CA ). 

Let the plane cutting off the segment be perpendicular to 
the plane of the paper, and let the latter plane be the plane 
through the axis of the hyperboloid which intersects the cutting 
plane at right angles in BB', and makes the hyperbolic 
segment BAB'. Let C be the centre of the hyperboloid (or 
the vertex of the enveloping cone). 

Let EF be that tangent to the hyperbolic section which is 
parallel to BB'. Let EF touch at A, and join CA. Then CA 
produced will bisect BB' at D, CA will be a semi-diameter of 
the hyperboloid, A will be the vertex of the segment, and AD 
its axis. Produce AC to A' and H, so that AC= CA' = A'H. 

Through EF draw a plane parallel to the base of the seg- 
ment. This plane will touch the hyperboloid at A. 

Then (1), if the base of the segment is at right angles to the 
axis of the hyperboloid, A will be the vertex, and AD the axis, 
of the hyperboloid as well as of the segment, and the base of the 
segment will be a circle on BB' as diameter. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



137 



(2) If the base of the segment is not perpendicular to the 
axis of the hyperboloid, the base will be an ellipse on BB' as 
major axis. [ pr P- 13 1 




N/ 



/ 



-Zv 

B' 



(AD) 



lAA'j 



Then we can draw a cylinder or a frustum of a cylinder 
EBB'F passing through the circle or ellipse about BB' and 
having AD for its axis; also we can describe a cone or a 
segment of a cone through the circle or ellipse and having A 
for its vertex. 

We have to prove that 
(segment ABB') : (cone or segment of cone ABB') = HD : A'D. 



138 ARCHIMEDES 

Let V be a cone such that 

V : (cone or segment of cone ABB') = HD : A 'D, (a) 

find we have to prove that V is equal to the segment. 

Now 
(cylinder or frustum EB') : (cone or segmt. of cone ABB f ) = 3:1. 

Therefore, by means of (a), 

TTT) 
(cylinder or frustum EB') :V = A'D: ?f- (0). 

O 

If the segment is not equal to F, it must either be greater 
or less. 

I. If possible, let the segment be greater than F. 

Inscribe and circumscribe to the segment figures made up 
of cylinders or frusta of cylinders, with axes along AD and all 
equal to one another, such that 

(circumscribed fig.) (inscr. fig.) < (segmt.) F, 
whence (inscribed figure) > F (7). 

Produce all the planes forming the bases of the cylinders or 
frusta of cylinders to meet the surface of the complete cylinder 
or frustum EB'. 

Then, if ND be the axis of the greatest cylinder or frustum 
in the circumscribed figure, the complete cylinder will be 
divided into cylinders or frusta each equal to this greatest 
cylinder or frustum. 

Let there be a number of straight lines a equal to A A ' and 
as many in number as the parts into which AD is divided by 
the bases of the cylinders or frusta. To each line a apply a 
rectangle which shall overlap it by a square, and let the greatest 
of the rectangles be equal to the rectangle AD . A'D and the 
least equal to the rectangle AL . A'L ; also let the sides of the 
overlapping squares 6, p, q,...l be in descending arithmetical 
progression. Thus 6, p, q,...l will be respectively equal to AD, 
AN, AM,...AL, and the rectangles (ab + ft 2 ), (ap+p*),...(al+F) 
will be respectively equal to AD . A'D, AN.A'N,...AL . A'L. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 139 

Suppose, further, that we have a series of spaces S each 
equal to the largest rectangle AD. A'D and as many in number 
as the diminishing rectangles. 

Comparing now the successive cylinders or frusta (1) in the 
complete cylinder or frustum EB' and (2) in the inscribed 
figure, beginning from the base of the segment, we have 

(first cylinder or frustum in EB') : (first in inscr. figure) 



= AD . A'D : AN. A'N, from the hyperbola, 
= S: (ap+p*). 
Again 

(second cylinder or frustum in EB') : (second in inscr. fig.) 
= BD*:QM* 
= AD.A'D:AM.A'M 



and so on. 

The last cylinder or frustum in the complete cylinder or 
frustum EB' has no cylinder or frustum corresponding to it in 
the inscribed figure. 

Combining the proportions, we have [Prop. 1] 

(cylinder or frustum EB') : (inscribed figure) 

= (sum of all the spaces S) : (ap + p*) 4- (at? 4- g 8 ) 4- . . . 

[Prop. 2] 



TTT) 

>A'D:-<T, since a = AA', b = AD, 

O 

>(EB'): V, by (B) above. 
Hence (inscribed figure) < V. 

But this is impossible, because, by (7) above, the inscribed 
figure is greater than F. 



140 ARCHIMEDES 

II. Next suppose, if possible, that the segment is less 
than V. 

In this case we circumscribe and inscribe figures such that 

(circumscribed fig.) (inscribed fig.) < F (segment), 
whence we derive 

V > (circumscribed figure) ............... (8). 

We now compare successive cylinders or frusta in the 
complete cylinder or frustum and in the circumscribed figure ; 
and we have 

(first cylinder or frustum in EB') : (first in circumscribed fig.) 

= 8:8 



(second in EB') : (second in circumscribed fig.) 

= S:(ap+p*), 
and so on. 

Hence [Prop. 1] 
(cylinder or frustum EB') : (circumscribed fig.) 

= (sum of all spaces 8) : (cub -f V) + (ap 4- p*) + . . . 

< (a + 6) : + [Prop. 2] 



<(EB')i F, by (ft) above. 

Hence the circumscribed figure is greater than F; which is 
impossible, by (8) above. 

Thus the segment is neither greater nor less than F, and is 
therefore equal to it. 

Therefore, by (a), 

(segment ABB') : (cone or segment of cone ABB') 

= (AD + SCA) : (AD+2CA). 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 141 



Propositions 27, 28, 29, 3O. 

(1) In any spheroid whose centre is C, if a plane meeting 
the axis cut off a segment not greater than half the spheroid and 
having A for its vertex and AD for its axis, and if A'D be the 
axis of the remaining segment of the spheroid, then 

(first segmt.) : (cone or segmt. of cone with same base and axis) 

= CA+A'D:A'D 
[= SCA - AD : 2CA - AD]. 

(2) As a particular case, if the plane passes through the 
centre, so that the segment is half the spheroid, half the spheroid 
is double of the cone or segment of a cone which has the same 
vertex and axis. 

Let the plane cutting off the segment be at right angles to 
the plane of the paper, and let the latter plane be the plane 
through the axis of the spheroid which intersects the cutting 
plane in BB' and makes the elliptic section ABA'B'. 

Let EF, E'F' be the two tangents to the ellipse which are 
parallel to BB 1 , let them touch it in A, A', and through the 
tangents draw planes parallel to the base of the segment. 
These planes will touch the spheroid at A, A', which will 
be the vertices of the two segments into which it is divided. 
Also A A' will pass through the centre C and bisect BB' 
in-D. 

Then (1) if the base of the segments be perpendicular to 
the axis of the spheroid, A, A! will be the vertices of the 
spheroid as well as of the segments, AA' will be the axis 
of the spheroid, and the base of the segments will be a circle on 
BB' as diameter ; 

(2) if the base of the segments be not perpendicular to the 
axis of the spheroid, the base of the segments will be an 
ellipse of which BB' is one axis, and AD, A'D will be the 
axes of the segments respectively. 



142 



ARCHIMEDES 



We can now draw a cylinder or a frustum of a cylinder 
EBB'F through the circle or ellipse about BB' and having AD 
for its axis; and we can also draw a cone or a segment of 
a cone passing through the circle or ellipse about BB' and 
having ^1 for its vertex. 








a 




a 









X 










a 8 







We have then to show that, if CA' be produced to H so 
thatCM'-jTir, 
(segment ABB') : (cone or segment of cone ABB') = /fZ) : A'D. 

Let F be such a cone that 

V : (cone or segment of cone ABB*) = HD : A'D . . . (a) ; 
and we have to show that the segment ABB' is equal to V. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 143 

But, since 
(cylinder or frustum EB') : (cone or segment of cone ABB') 

= 3:1, 
we have, by the aid of (a), 

ffD 

(cylinder or frustum EB') : V = A'D : ^p (ft). 

Now, if the segment ABB' is not equal to F, it must 
be either greater or less. 

I. Suppose, if possible, that the segment is greater 
than V. 

Let figures be inscribed and circumscribed to the segment 
consisting of cylinders or frusta of cylinders, with axes along 
AD and all equal to one another, such that 

(circumscribed fig.) (inscribed fig.) < (segment) F, 
whence it follows that 

(inscribed fig.) > F (7). 

Produce all the planes forming the bases of the cylinders or 
frusta to meet the surface of the complete cylinder or frustum 
EB'. Thus, if ND be the axis of the greatest cylinder or 
frustum of a cylinder in the circumscribed figure, the complete 
cylinder or frustum EB' will be divided into cylinders or frusta 
of cylinders each equal to the greatest of those in the circum- 
scribed figure. 

Take straight lines da each equal to A'D and as many in 
number as the parts into which AD is divided by the bases of 
the cylinders or frusta, and measure da along da' equal to AD. 
It follows that aa' = 2CD. 

Apply to each of the lines a'd rectangles with height equal 
to ad, and draw the squares on each of the lines ad as in 
the figure. Let 8 denote the area of each complete rectangle. 

From the first rectangle take away a gnomon with breadth 
equal to AN (i.e. with each end of a length equal to AN) ; 
take away from the second rectangle a gnomon with breadth 
equal to AM, and so on, the last rectangle having no gnomon 
taken from it. 



144 ARCHIMEDES 

Then 

the first gnomon A'D . AD -ND . (A'D - AN) 



= AN.A'N. 
Similarly, 

the second gnomon = AM. A'M y 
and so on. 

And the last gnomon (that in the last rectangle but one) is 
equal to AL . A'L. 

Also, after the gnomons are taken away from the successive 
rectangles, the remainders (which we will call R 19 .R a ,... R n , 
where n is the number of rectangles and accordingly R n = 8) 
are rectangles applied to straight lines each of length aa! and 
"exceeding by squares" whose sides are respectively equal 
to DN, DM,... DA. 

For brevity, let DN be denoted by x, and aa or 2CD by c, 
so that R v = cx + x\ R 9 = c . 2x + (2x)\ . . . 

Then, comparing successively the cylinders or frusta of 
cylinders (1) in the complete cylinder or frustum EB' and 
(2) in the inscribed figure, we have 

(first cylinder or frustum in EB') : (first in inscribed fig.) 



= AD.A'D:AN.A'N 
= 8 : (first gnomon) ; 
(second cylinder or frustum in EB') : (second in inscribed fig.) 

= 8 : (second gnomon), 
and so on. 

The last of the cylinders or frusta in the cylinder or 
frustum EB' has none corresponding to it in the inscribed 
figure, and there is no corresponding gnomon. 

Combining the proportions, we have [by Prop. 1] 
(cylinder or frustum EB') : (inscribed fig.) 

= (sum of all spaces S) : (sum of gnomons). 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 145 

Now the differences between 8 and the successive gnomons 
are R lt R 2 , ... R n , while 

R l = ex + a? 9 



where 6 = nx = AD. 
Hence [Prop. 2] 

(sum of all spaces S) : (JZ t + JR.+ ... + # n ) < (c +6) : (| + |) . 
It follows that 
(sum of all spaces $) : (sum of gnomons) > (c + 6) : ( + - - ) 

\6 O J 

>">? 

Thus (cylinder or frustum JE7T) : (inscribed fig.) 

>* 

> (cylinder or frustum EB') : V, 
from (j3) above. 

Therefore (inscribed fig.) < F ; 

which is impossible, by (7) above. 

Hence the segment ABB' is not greater than V. 

II. If possible, let the segment ABB / be less than F. 

We then inscribe and circumscribe figures such that 

(circumscribed fig.) (inscribed fig.) < F (segment), 
whence F > (circumscribed fig.) (8). 

In this case we compare the cylinders or frusta in (EB f ) 
with those in the circumscribed figure. 

Thus 
(first cylinder or frustum in EB') : (first in circumscribed fig.) 

= S:S; 
(second in EB') : (second in circumscribed fig.) 

= S : (first gnomon), 
and so on. 

H. A. 10 



146 ARCHIMEDES 

Lastly (last in EB') : (last in circumscribed fig.) 

= 8 : (last gnomon). 
Now 

[S + (all the gnomons)} = nS - (R^- R. 2 + ... 

And nflf:B 1 + -B a + ...+-R-i>(c + 6): f| + gj, [Prop. 2] 

so that 

/c 26\ 
nS : {8 + (all the gnomons)} < (c + b) : f ^ + -g- J 

It follows that, if we combine the above proportions as in 
Prop. 1, we obtain 

(cylinder or frustum EB') : (circumscribed fig.) 



< (EB') : V, by (ft) above. 

Hence the circumscribed figure is greater than V\ which is 
impossible, by (8) above. 

Thus, since the segment ABB' is neither greater nor less 
than V, it is equal to it ; and the proposition is proved. 

(2) The particular case [Props. 27, 28] where the segment 
is half the spheroid differs from the above in that the distance 
CD or c/2 vanishes, and the rectangles cb + b 2 are simply squares 
(6 2 ), so that the gnomons are simply the differences between 6* 
and # 2 , 6 2 and (2#)' 2 , and so on. 



Instead therefore of Prop. 2 we use the Lemma to Prop. 2, 
Cor. 1, given above [On Spirals, Prop. 10], and instead of the 

ratio (c + 6) : ( | + -g J we obtain the ratio 3 : 2, whence 

(segment ABB') : (cone or segment of cone ABB') = 2:1. 

[This result can also be obtained by simply substituting 
CA for AD in the ratio (3CA -AD) : (2CA - AD).] 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 



147 



Propositions 31, 32. 

If a plane divide a spheroid into two unequal segments, and 
if AN, A'N be the axes of the lesser and greater segments 
respectively, while C is the centre of the spheroid, then 
(greater segmt.) : (cone or segmt of cone with same base and aods) 

= CA + AN:AN.' 

Let the plane dividing the spheroid be that through PP' 
perpendicular to the plane of the paper, and let the latter plane 
be that through the axis of the spheroid which intersects the 
cutting plane in PP' and makes the elliptic section PAP' A'. 




Draw the tangents to the ellipse which are parallel to PP'; 
let them touch the ellipse at A, A ', and through the tangents 
draw planes parallel to the base of the segments. These planes 
will touch the spheroid at A, A' y the line AA' will pass 
through the centre G and bisect PP' in N 9 while AN, AN will 
be the axes of the segments. 

Then (1) if the cutting plane be perpendicular to the axis 
of the spheroid, A A 1 will be that axis, and A, A' will be the 
vertices of the spheroid as well as of the segments. Also the 
sections of the spheroid by the cutting plane and all planes 
parallel to it will be circles. 

(2) If the cutting plane be not perpendicular to the axis, 



-m 9 



148 ARCHIMEDES 

the base of the segments will be an ellipse of which PP' is an 
axis, and the sections of the spheroid by all planes parallel 
to the cutting plane will be similar ellipses. 

Draw a plane through G parallel to the base of the segments 
and meeting the plane of the paper in BB'. 

Construct three cones or segments of cones, two having A 
for their common vertex and the plane sections through PP', 
BB f for their respective bases, and a third having the plane 
section through PP' for its base and A' for its vertex. 

Produce CA to H and CA' to H' so that 

A'H'=CA. 



We have then to prove that 

(segment A'PP') : (cone or segment of cone A'PP') 

= CA + AN:AN 
= NH : AN. 

Now half the spheroid is double of the cone or segment of a 
cone ABB' [Props. 27, 28]. Therefore 

(the spheroid) = 4 (cone or segment of cone ABB'). 
But 

(cone or segmt. of cone ABB') : (cone or segmt. of cone APP') 
= (CA :AN).(BC*:PN*) 
= (CA :AN).(CA.CA':AN.A'N)...(a). 
If we measure AK along A A' so that 

AK:AC= AC: AN, 

we have AK.A'N : AG. A'N=CA : AN, 

and the compound ratio in (a) becomes 

(AK. A'N : CA . A'N).(CA . CA' : AN.A'N), 

ie. AK.CA'-.AN.A'N. 

Thus 

(cone or segmt. of cone ABB') : (cone or segmt. of cone APP') 

= AK.CA'-.AN.A'N. 



ON CONOIDS AND SPHEROIDS. 149 

But (cone or segment of cone APP') : (segment APP') 

= A'N:NH' [Props. 29, 30] 

= AN.A'N:AN.NH'. 
Therefore, ex aequali, 

(cone or segment of cone ABB') : (segment APP 1 ) 

= AK.CA' -.AN.NH', 
so that (spheroid) : (segment APP') 

= HH'.AK:AN.NH', 
since HH' = 4>CA'. 

Hence (segment A'PP') : (segment APP') 

= (HE 1 .AK-AN. NH') : AN . NH' 

= (AK . NH + NH' . NK) : AN. NH'. 
Further, 

(segment APP') : (cone or segment of cone APP') 
= NH':A'N 

= AN.NH':AN.A'N, 
and 

(cone or segmt. of cone APP') : (cone or segmt. of cone A'PP') 

= AN : A'N 
= AN.A'N: A'N 3 . 

From the last three proportions we obtain, ex aequali, 
(segment A'PP') : (cone or segment of cone A'PP') 
= (AK. NH + NH' . NK) : A 'N* 
= (AK. NH + NH' . NK) : (CA* + NH' . CN) 
= (AK.NH + NH' . NK) -.(AK.AN + NH' . CN) . . .( 

But 
AK.NH : AK.AN^NH : AN 

= CA+AN:AN 
CA:OA 



= HK:CA 

= HK-NH:CA-AN 
= NK:CN 
^NH'.NK -.NH'.CN. 



150 ARCHIMEDES. 

Hence the ratio in (/3) is equal to the ratio 

AK.NH :AK.AN, or NH : AN. 
Therefore 

(segment A'PP') : (cone or segment of cone A'PP') 

= NH:AN 
= CA+AN: AN. 

[If (#, y) be the coordinates of P referred to the conjugate 
diameters AA' t BB' as axes of x, y, and if 2a, 2b be the lengths 
of the diameters respectively, we have, since 

(spheroid) (lesser segment) = (greater segment), 



and the above proposition is the geometrical proof of the truth 
of this equation where x, y are connected by the equation 


            -->
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
