<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Quadrature of the Parabola</title>
                <author>Archimedes</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thomas Heath</persName>
                    <resp>translator</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This electronic edition was prepared by Neel Smith, and is licensed under the
                    Creative Commons NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License. Its markup validates
                    against version P5 of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines, and follows the
                    markup conventions of the "Free Greek" project.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This text is based on pages 233-252 of the Dover reprint edition of Heath's
                    original 1897 publication now in the public domain: <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>Thomas Heath</editor>
                            <title>The Works of Archimedes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mineola, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dover</publisher>
                                <date>2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope
                                type="pp">233-252</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- 
            

QUADRATUKE OF THE PAEABOLA. 



"ARCHIMEDES to Dositheus greeting. 

" When I heard that Conon, who was my friend in his life- 
time, was dead, but that you were acquainted with Conon and 
withal versed in geometry, while I grieved for the loss not only 
of a friend but of an admirable mathematician, I set myself the 
task of communicating to you, as I had intended to send to 
Conon, a certain geometrical theorem which had not been 
investigated before but has now been investigated by me, and 
which I first discovered by means of mechanics and then 
exhibited by means of geometry. Now some of the earlier 
geometers tried to prove it possible to find a rectilineal area 
equal to a given circle and a given segment of a circle ; and 
after that they endeavoured to square the area bounded by the 
section of the whole cone* and a straight line, assuming lemmas 
not easily conceded, so that it was recognised by most people 
that the problem was not solved. But I am not aware that 
any one of my predecessors has attempted to square the 
segment bounded by a straight line and a section of a right- 
angled cone [a parabola], of which problem I have now dis- 
covered the solution. For it is here shown that every segment 
bounded by a. straight line and a section of a right-angled cone 
[a parabola] is four-thirds of the triangle which has the same base 
and equal height with the segment, and for the demonstration 

* There appears to be some corruption here : the expression in the text is 
ras oXou roO K&VOV TO/MI*, and it is not easy to give a natural and intelligible 
meaning to it. The section of ' the whole cone ' might perhaps mean a section 
cutting right through it, i.e. an ellipse, and the ' straight line ' might be an axis 
or a diameter. But Heiberg objects to the suggestion to read rat dvywlov 
xcfrou ro/iai , in view of the addition of *al etftofaj, on the ground that the former 
expression always signifies the whole of an ellipse, never a segment of it 
(Quaettiones Archimedeae, p. 149). 



234 ARCHIMEDES 

of this property the following lemma is assumed: that the 
excess by which the greater of (two) unequal areas exceeds 
the less can, by being added to itself, be made to exceed any 
given finite area. The earlier geometers have also used this 
lemma ; for it is by the use of this same lemma that they have 
shown that circles are to one another in the duplicate ratio of 
their diameters, and that spheres are to one another in the 
triplicate ratio of their diameters, and further that every 
pyramid is one third part of the prism which has the same base 
with the pyramid and equal height; also, that every cone is 
one third part of the cylinder having the same base as the cone 
and equal height they proved by assuming a certain lemma 
similar to that aforesaid. And, in the result, each of the afore- 
said theorems has been accepted* no less than those proved 
without the lemma. As therefore my work now published has 
satisfied the same test as the propositions referred to, I have 
written out the proof and send it to you, first as investigated 
by means of mechanics, and afterwards too as demonstrated by 
geometry. Prefixed are, also, the elementary propositions in 
conies which are of service in the proof (o-ro^eia iccovi/ca %piav 
es rav dirroSeigw). Farewell." 



Proposition 1. 

If from a point on a para- 
bola a straight line be drawn 
which is either itself the axis or 
parallel to the axis, as PV, and 
if QQ' be a chord parallel to 
the tangent to the parabola at P 
and meeting PV in V t then 

QF= FQ'. 

Conversely, if QF= VQ', the 
chord QQ' Ml be parallel to the 
tangent at P. 

* The Greek of this passage is : ffv^aivei 5t rQv irpocipwtvw 0ewpr)fj.druv 
IKOGTW w&tv jjffffov r&v Avcv rofrrov rov Xi}/x/uarot dvodctciyfjifrw iririffTVKtvai. 
Here it would seem that ireircorret/K^ac must be wrong and that the passive 
should have been used. 




QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 235 



Proposition 2. 

If in a parabola QQ' be a chord parallel to the tangent at P t 
and if a straight line be drawn through P which is either itself 
the aods or parallel to the axis, and which meets QQ' in V and 
the tangent at Q to the parabola in T, then 

PV=PT. 




Proposition 3. 

If from a point on a parabola a straight line be drawn 
which is either itself the axis or parallel to the axis, as PV t 
and if from two other points Q, Q' on the parabola straight 
lines be drawn parallel to the tangent at P and meeting PV in 
V y V respectively, then 



" And these propositions are proved in the elements of conies*" 

Proposition 4. 

If Qq be the base of any segment of a parabola, and P the 
verteac of the segment, and if the diameter through any other point 
R meet Qq in and QP (produced if necessary) in F, then 

QV: VO = OF:FR. 

Draw the ordinate RW to PV, meeting QP in K. 
* i.e. in the treatises on conies by Euolid and Aristaeus. 



236 ARCHIMEDES 



Then PV:PW = QV':RW>; 

whence, by parallels, 




In other words, PQ, PF, PK are in continued proportion; 
therefore 



= PQPF:PFPK 

- QF : KF. 
Hence, by parallels, 

QV: VO = OF:FR 

[It is easily seen that this equation is equivalent to a change of 
axes of coordinates from the tangent and diameter to new axes 
consisting of the chord Qq (as axis of #, say) and the diameter 
through Q (as axis of y). 

g 

For, if QF = a, PF= , where p is the parameter of the 
ordinates to PF. 

Thus, if QO = x, and RO = y, the above result gives 

a OF 

x-a~ OF-y* 
a 

, a OF X 'p 

whence ^ = = *- , 

2a-x y y 

or = 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 237 



Proposition 5. 

If Qq be the base of any segment of a parabola, P the vertex 
of the segment, and PV its diameter, and if the diameter of the 
parabola through any other point R meet Qq in and the 
tangent at Q in E, then 

QO:Oq = ER:RO. 
Let the diameter through R meet QP in F. 




Then, by Prop. 4, 

QV: VO=OF:FJR. 

Since QV= Vq, it follows that 

QV:qO = OF:OR (1). 

Also, if VP meet the tangent in T, 

PT = PV, and therefore EF=OF. 
Accordingly, doubling the antecedents in (1), we have 

Qq:qO = OE: OR, 
whence QO : Oq = ER:RO. 



238 



ARCHIMEDES 



Propositions 6, 7*. 

Suppose a lever A OB placed horizontally and supported at 
its middle point 0. Let a triangle BCD in which the angle C is 
right or obtuse be suspended from B and 0, so that C is attached 
to and CD is in the same vertical line with 0. Then, if P be 
such an area as, when suspended from A, will keep the system in 
equilibrium, 



Take a point E on OB such that BE=20E, and draw EFH 
parallel to OCD meeting BC, BD in F, H respectively. Let G 
be the middle point of FH. 




Then G is the centre of gravity of the triangle BCD. 

Hence, if the angular points B, C be set free and the 
triangle be suspended by attaching jP to E t the triangle will 
hang in the same position as before, because EFG is a vertical 
straight line. "For this is proved f." 

Therefore, as before, there will be equilibrium. 
Thus P:&BCD=OE:AO 

= 1:3, 
or P 

* In Prop. 6 Archimedes takes the separate case in which the angle BCD of 
the triangle is a right angle so that C coincides with O in the figure and F with 
E. He then proves, in Prop. 7, the same property for the triangle in which 
BCD is an obtuse angle, by treating the triangle as the difference between two 
right-angled triangles BOD, BOC and using the result of Prop. 6. I have com- 
bined the two propositions in one proof, for the sake of brevity. The same 
remark applies to the propositions following Props. 6, 7. 

t Doubtless in the lost book irepl vyw. Of. the Introduction, Chapter II., 
ad fin. 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 



239 



Propositions 8, 9. 

Suppose a lever AOB placed horizontally and supported at 
its middle point 0. Let a triangle BCD, right-angled or obtuse- 
angled at C, be suspended from the points B, E on OB, the 
angular point C being so attached to E that the side CD is in the 
same vertical line with E. Let Q be an area such that 

AO :OE = &BCD:Q. 
Then, if an area P suspended from A keep the system in 

equilibrium, 

P<ABCDbut>Q. 

Take G the centre of gravity of the triangle BCD, and draw 
OH parallel to DC, i.e. vertically, meeting BO in H. 

A o_ E H B 





We may now suppose the triangle BCD suspended from H, 
and, since there is equilibrium, 

ABCD :P = AO: OH (1), 

whence P<ABCD. 

Also &BCD:Q = AO: OE. 

Therefore, by (1), ABCD : Q >ABCD : P, 
and P > Q. 

Propositions 1O, 11. 

Suppose a lever AOB placed horizontally and supported at 0, 
its middle point. Let CDEF be a trapezium which can be so 
placed that its parallel sides CD, FE are vertical, while C is 
vertically below 0, and the other sides CF, DE meet in B. Let 
EF meet BO in H, and let the trapezium be suspended by attaching 
F to H and G to 0. Further, suppose Q to be an area such that 
+ AO: OH = (trapezium CDEF) : Q. 



240 



ARCHIMEDES 



Then, if P be the area which, when suspended from A, keeps the 
system in equilibrium, 

P<Q. 

The same is true in the particular case where the angles at 
C y F are right, and consequently C, F coincide with 0, H 



Divide OH in K so that 




Draw KG parallel to OD, and let G be the middle point of 
the portion of KG intercepted within the trapezium. Then G 
is the centre of gravity of the trapezium [On, the equilibrium of 
planes, I. 15]. 

Thus we may suppose the trapezium suspended from K, and 
the equilibrium will remain undisturbed. 

Therefore 

AO : OK = (trapezium CDEF) : P, 

and, by hypothesis, 

AO : OH = (trapezium CDEF) : Q. 
Since OK< OH, it follows that 



Propositions 12, 13. 

If the trapezium CDEF be placed as in the last propositions, 
except that CD is vertically below a point L on OB instead of 
being below 0, and the trapezium is suspended from L, H, 
suppose that Q, R are areas such that 

AO : OH = (trapezium CDEF) : Q, 
and AO : OL = (trapezium CDEF) : K 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 



241 



If tlien an area P suspended from A keep the system in 
equilibrium, 

P > R but < Q. 

Take the centre of gravity of the trapezium, as in the 
last propositions, and let the line through G parallel to DC 
meet OB in K. 



L K 





Then we may suppose the trapezium suspended from K, 
and there will still be equilibrium. 

Therefore (trapezium GDEF) : P = AO : OK. 

Hence 

(trapezium GDEF) : P > (trapezium CDEF) : Q, 

but < (trapezium CDEF) : R. 

It follows that P < Q but > R. 



Propositions 14, 15. 

Let Qq be the base of any segment of a parabola. Then, if 
two lines be drawn from Q, q, each parallel to the axis of the 
parabola and on the same side of Qq as the segment is, either 

(1) the angles so formed at Q, q are both right angles, or 

(2) one is acute and the other obtuse. In the latter case let 
the angle at q be the obtuse angle. 

Divide Qq into any number of equal parts at the points 
O lt 2 , ... O n . Draw through q, O lf 2 , ... O n diameters of the 
parabola meeting the tangent at Q in E t E ly E Zt ... E n and the 
parabola itself in q, R lt R,, ... R n . Join QR 19 QR*, ... QR n 
meeting qE, 



H. A. 



16 



242 



ARCHIMEDES 



Let the diameters Eq, E^O^ ... E n O n meet a straight line 
QOA drawn through Q perpendicular to the diameters in the 
points 0, H!, H z , ... H n respectively. (In the particular case 
where Qq is itself perpendicular to the diameters q will coincide 
with 0, Oi with H 19 and so on.) 

It is required to prove that 

(1) AEqQ< 3(sum of trapezia F0 1} F&, . . . F n ^0 n and&E n O n Q), 

(2) AEqQ>S(sumoftrapeziaR l O Z) B 2 By . . . Rn^ 



H 9 Hn-l H Q 



Pn+J 




Suppose AO made equal to OQ, and conceive QOA as a 
lever placed horizontally and supported at 0. Suppose the 
triangle EqQ suspended from OQ in the position drawn, and 
suppose that the trapezium E0 l in the position drawn is 
balanced by an area P l suspended from A, the trapezium Efi* 
in the position drawn is balanced by the area P 2 suspended 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 243 

from A, and so on, the triangle E n O n Q being in like manner 
balanced by P n+1 . 

Then P 1 + P 3 + ... + P n +i will balance the whole triangle 
EqQ as drawn, and therefore 

Pr + P,+ ... + P w -4AJBljQ. [Props. 6, 7] 
Again AO : 0^ = QO : OH, 

= Qq:q0 1 
= E& : 0& [by means of Prop. 5] 

= (trapezium EOi) : (trapezium 
whence [Props. 10, 11] 



Next AO:OH 1 = E l O l :0 1 R l 

= (E 1 0,):(R 1 3 ) .............. (a), 

while AO : OH a = E t 0. t : OA 



and, since (o) and (ft) are simultaneously true, we have, by 
Props. 12, 13, 



Similarly it may be proved that 



and so on. 

Lastly [Props. 8, 9] 

AE n O n Q>P n+1 >AR n O n Q. 
By addition, we obtain 
(1) (FOJ+(F&)+. .. +(F n _ l O n )+ AE n O n Q> P, 



or 



< P l + P a + . . . + P n+1 , a fortiori, 
<$AEqQ, 

or AEqQ > 3 (^0, + R*0 t +...+ -K B _,O n + A KO n Q). 

162 



244 



ARCHIMEDES 



Proposition 16. 

Suppose Qq to be the base of a parabolic segment, q being 
not more distant than Qfrom the vertex of the parabola. Draw 
through q the straight line qE parallel to the axis of the parabola 
to meet the tangent at Q in E. It is required to prove that 

(area of segment) = A EqQ. 

For, if not, the area of the segment must be either greater 
or less than A EqQ. 

I. Suppose the area of the 
segment greater than A EqQ. 
Then the excess can, if con- 
tinually added to itself, be 
made to exceed A EqQ. And 
it is possible to find a submul- 
tiple of the triangle EqQ less 
than the said excess of the 
segment over A EqQ. 

Let the triangle -FyQ be such 
a submultiple of the triangle 
EqQ. Divide Eq into equal 
parts each equal to qF, and let 
all the points of division in- 
cluding F be joined to Q meet- e 
ing the parabola in R lt R 29 ... 

R n respectively. Through R l9 R t ... R n draw diameters of the 
parabola meeting qQ in O lf 2 , ... O n respectively. 

Let 0^ meet QR 2 in F,. 

Let 2 R* meet QR l in A and QR B in F z . 

Let B R B meet QJ? 2 in D 2 and QR 4 in F 9 , and so on. 



or 




We have, by hypothesis, 

A FqQ < (area of segment) - 
(area of segment) AFqQ > J &EqQ ......... (a). 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. . 245 

Now, since all the parts of qE, as qF and the rest, are equal, 
0& = R 1 F 19 2 A = DA = RJF*, and so on ; therefore 



But 

(area of segment) < (F0 l +F& + ... +F n _ 1 n + A E n O n Q). 
Subtracting, we have 
(area of segment) - A FqQ < (R& + Rf)* + ... 



whence, a fortiori, by (a), 

i AEqQ < (R& + R, 2 3 + ... + Rn-iO n + AR n O n Q). 
But this is impossible, since [Props. 14, 15] 



Therefore 

(area of segment) :)> %&EqQ. 

II. If possible, suppose the area of the segment less than 



Take a submultiple of the triangle EqQ, as the triangle 
FqQ, less than the excess of %AEqQ over the area of the 
segment, and make the same construction as before. 

Since A FqQ < $AEqQ (area of segment), 
it follows that 
A FqQ + (area of segment) < A EqQ 

< (F0 l + F& + . . . + F n ^0 n + AE n O n Q). 

[Props. 14, 15] 

Subtracting from each side the area of the segment, we have 
A^Q<(sum of spaces qFR lt R^F^, ... E n R n Q) 

< (FO, + F,D, + . . . + F n ^D n ^ + A E n R n Q\ a fortiori; 
which is impossible, because, by ()8) above, 



Hence (area of segment) <fc %AEqQ. 

Since then the area of the segment is neither less nor 
greater than JA-fyQ, it is equal to it. 



246 



ARCHIMEDES 



Proposition 17. 

It is now manifest that the area of any segment of a 
parabola is four-thirds of the triangle which has the same base 
as the segment and equal height. 

Let Qq be the base of the segment, P its vertex. Then 
PQq is the inscribed triangle with the 
same base as the segment and equal 
height. 

Since P is the vertex* of the seg- 
ment, the diameter through P bisects 
Qq. Let F be the point of bisection. 

Let FP, and qE drawn parallel to 
it, meet the tangent at Q in T t E re- 
spectively. 

Then, by parallels, 



PF=PT, 
FF=2PF. 




and PF=PT, [Prop. 2] 

so that 

Hence 
But, by Prop. 16, the area of the segment is equal to 

Therefore (area of segment) = f A PQq. 



DBF. "In segments bounded by a straight line and any 
curve I call the straight line the base, and the height the 
greatest perpendicular drawn from the curve to the base of the 
segment, and the vertex the point from which the greatest 
perpendicular is drawn. 7 ' 

* It is curious that Archimedes uses the terms base and vertex of a segment 
here, but gives the definition of them later (at the end of the proposition). 
Moreover he assumes the converse of the property proved in Prop. 18. 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 247 

Proposition 18. 

If Qq be the base of a segment of a parabola, and V the 
middle point of Qq> and if the diameter through V meet the 
curve in P, then P is the vertex of the segment. 




For Qq is parallel to the tangent at P [Prop. 1]. Therefore, 
of all the perpendiculars which can be drawn from points on the 
segment to the base Qq, that from P is the greatest. Hence, 
by the definition, P is the vertex of the segment. 

Proposition 19. 

// Qq be a chord of a parabola bisected in V by the diameter 
PV, and if RM be a diameter bisecting QV in M, and RW 
be the ordinate from R to PV, then 



// / 




a 
For, by the property of the parabola, 



so that PV = 4>PW, 

whence PV=$RM. 



248 



ARCHIMEDES 



Proposition 2O. 

If Qq be the base, and P the vertex, of a parabolic segment, 
then the triangle PQq is greater than half the segment PQq. 

For the chord Qq is parallel to the tangent at P, and the 
triangle PQq is half the parallelogram 
formed by Qq, the tangent at P, and the 
diameters through Q, q. 

Therefore the triangle PQq is greater 
than half the segment. 

COR. It follows that it is possible 
to inscribe in the segment a polygon such 
that the segments left over are together 
less than any assigned area. 




Proposition 21. 

If Qq be the base, and P the vertex, of any parabolic 
segment, and if R be the vertex of the segment cut off by PQ, 
then 



The diameter through R will bisect the chord PQ, and 
therefore also QV, where PV is the 
diameter bisecting Qq. Let the dia- 
meter through R bisect PQ in Y and 
QViaM. JoinPM. 

By Prop. 19, 



Also 

Therefore 

and 

Hence 

and 



PF=271f. 
, YM=2RY, 
APQJfaT=2APJJQ. 
A PQ V = 4 A PRQ, 




QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 249 

Also, if RW, the ordinate from R to PV, be produced to 
meet the curve again in r, 



and the same proof shows that 
&PQq 



Proposition 22. 

If there be a series of areas A, B,C, D, ... each of which is 
four times the next in order, and if the largest, A, be equal to the 
triangle PQq inscribed in a parabolic segment PQq and having 
the same base with it and equal height, then 

(A + B+C + D + ...)< (area of segment PQq). 

For, since APQ? = 8 APJJQ = 8 AP^r, where R, r are the 
vertices of the segments cut off by PQ, 
Pq, as in the last proposition, 




Therefore, since A PQq = A, 
AP&B+ APgr=B. 

In like manner we prove that the 
triangles similarly inscribed in the re- 
maining segments are together equal to 
the area (7, and so on. 

Therefore A+B + C + D + ... is equal to the area of a 
certain inscribed polygon, and is therefore less than the area of 
the segment. 



Proposition 23. 

Given a series of areas A, B, C,D t ... Z,of which A is the 
greatest, and each is equal to four times the next in order y then 



250 ARCHIMEDES 

Take areas b, c, d, ... such that 



Then, since 
and 

Similarly 
Therefore 



But 



d = D, and so on. 
6 = ^B, 
B = A, 



C + c = 5. 



Therefore, by subtraction, 



or 



QUADRATURE OF THE PARABOLA. 



251 



The algebraical equivalent of this result is of course 

^-(iM 



Proposition 24. 

Every segment bounded by a parabola and a chord Qq is 
equal to four-thirds of the triangle which has the same base as 
the segment and equal height. 

Suppose K=$APQq, 

where P is the vertex of the segment ; and we have then to 
prove that the area of the segment is 
equal to K. 

For, if the segment be not equal to 
K, it must either be greater or less. 

I. Suppose the area of the segment 
greater than K. 

If then we inscribe in the segments 
cut off by PQ t Pq triangles which have 
the same base and equal height, i.e. 
triangles with the same vertices R, r as 
those of the segments, and if in the 
remaining segments we inscribe triangles in the same manner, 
and so on, we shall finally have segments remaining whose sum 
is less than the area by which the segment PQq exceeds K. 

Therefore the polygon so formed must be greater than the 
area K ; which is impossible, since [Prop. 23] 




where A = A PQq. 

Thus the area of the segment cannot be greater than K. 

II. Suppose, if possible, that the area of the segment is 
less than K. 



252 ARCHIMEDES. 



If then APQq = A, J5= \A, = J5, and so on, until we 
arrive at an area X such that X is less than the difference 
between K and the segment, we have 

f4 [Prop. 23] 



Now, since K exceeds A + B + C+... + Xby an area less 
than X, and the area of the segment by an area greater than X, 
it follows that 

A +B+C+ ... +X>(the segment); 
which is impossible, by Prop. 22 above. 
Hence the segment is not less than K. 
Thus, since the segment is neither greater nor less than K, 

(area of segment PQq) = K = 




            -->
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
