<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Book of Lemmas</title>
                <author>Archimedes</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thomas Heath</persName>
                    <resp>translator</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This electronic edition was prepared by Neel Smith, and is licensed under the
                    Creative Commons NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License. Its markup validates
                    against version P5 of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines, and follows the
                    markup conventions of the "Free Greek" project.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This text is based on pages 301-318 of the Dover reprint edition of Heath's
                    original 1897 publication now in the public domain: <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>Thomas Heath</editor>
                            <title>The Works of Archimedes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mineola, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dover</publisher>
                                <date>2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope
                                type="pp">301-318</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- 
            

BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



Proposition 1 . 

If two circles touch at A, and ifBD, EF be parallel diameters 
in them, ADF is a straight line. 

[The proof in the text only applies to the particular case 
where the diameters are perpendicular to the radius to the 
point of contact, but it is easily adapted to the more general 
case by one small change only.] 

Let 0, C be the centres of the circles, and let OC be joined 
and produced to A. Draw DH parallel to AO meeting OF 
inH. 




Then, since 
and OF=OA, 

we have, by subtraction, 



Therefore 



Z HDF - HFD. 



302 



ARCHIMEDES 



Thus both the triangles CAD, HDF are isosceles, and the 
third angles ACD, DHF in each are equal. Therefore the 
equal angles in each are equal to one another, and 



Add to each the angle CDF, and it follows that 



= (two right angles). 
Hence ADF is a straight line. 
The same proof applies if the circles touch externally*. 



Proposition 2. 

Let AB be the diameter of a semicircle, and let the tangents 
to it at B and at any other point D on it meet in T. If now DE 
be drawn perpendicular to AB, and if AT, DE meet in F, 

DF=FE. 

Produce AD to meet BT produced in H. Then the angle 
ADB in the semicircle is right; therefore the angle BDH is 
also right. And TB, TD are equal. 




Therefore T is the centre of the semicircle on BU as 
diameter, which passes through D. 

Hence HT=TB. 

And, since DE, HB are parallel, it follows that DF= FE. 

* Pappus assumes the result of this proposition in connexion with the 
<fy>/3ijAof (p. 214, ed. Hultsch), and he proves it for the case where the circles 
touch externally (p. 840). 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



303 



Proposition 3. 

Let P be any point on a segment of a circle whose base is 
AB, and let PN be perpendicular to AB. Take D on AB so 
that AN = ND. If now PQ be an arc equal to the arc PA, and 

BQ be joined, 

BQ, BD shall be equal*. 




3omPA,PQ,PD,DQ. 

* The segment iu the figure of the MS. appears to have been a semicircle, 
though the proposition is equally true of any segment. But the case where the 
segment is a semicircle brings the proposition into close connexion with a 
proposition in Ptolemy's fieydXy 0-frragtt, I. 9 (p. 31, ed. Halma; cf. the repro- 
duction in Cantor's Gesch. d. Matliematik, I. (1894), p. 389). Ptolemy's object is 
to connect by an equation the lengths of the chord of an arc and the chord of half 
the arc. Substantially his procedure is as follows. Suppose AP t PQ to be 
equal arcs, AB the diameter through A ; and let AP, PQ, AQ, PB, QB be joined. 
Measure BD along BA equal to BQ. The perpendicular PN is now drawn, and 
it is proved that PA=PD, and AN= ND. 

Then AN^(BA -/?Z>) = J (DA - BQ) = J (BA - \'l*A* - A <?*). 
And, by similar triangles, AN : AP=AP : AB. 

Therefore AP*=AB . AN 

= i (AB - \lAB* ~AQ*) . AB. 

This gives AP in terms of AQ and the known diameter AB. If we divide by 
AB 2 throughout, it is seen at once that the proposition gives a geometrical 
proof of the formula 

sin 3 ^j = J (1 - cos o). 

The case where the segment is a semicircle recalls also the method used by 
Archimedes at the beginning of the second part of Prop. 3 of the Measurement 
of a circle. It is there proved that, in the figure above, 



or, if we divide the first two terms of the proposition by AB, 
( 1 + cos a)/sin a = cot ~ . 



304 ARCHIMEDES 

Then, since the arcs PA, PQ are equal, 

PA=PQ. 
But, since AN = ND, and the angles at N are right, 

PA=PD. 
Therefore 
and 

Now, since A, P, Q, B are concyclic, 

Z P4D 4- Z PQB = (two right angles), 
whence Z PD4 + Z PQB = (two right angles) 



Therefore Z PQ5 - 

and, since the parts, the angles PQD, PDQ, are equal, 



and 



Proposition 4. 

IfAB be the diameter of a semicircle and N any point on AB % 
and if semicircles be described within the first semicircle and 
having AN, BN as diameters respectively, the figure included 
between the circumferences of the three semicircles is "what 
Archimedes called an ap/Si/Xo?*"; and its area is equal to the 
circle on PN a* diameter, where PN is perpendicular to AB 
and meets the original semicircle in P. 

For AB 9 - AIT + NB* + 2AN . NB 



But circles (or semicircles) are to one another as the squares of 
their radii (or diameters). 

* &pfa\ot is literally ' a shoemaker's knife.' Cf. note attached to the remarks 
on the Liber A$$umptorum in the Introduction, Chapter II. 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



305 



Hence 
(semicircle on 



of semicircles on AN, NB) 
+ 2 (semicircle on PN). 




That is, the circle on PN as diameter is equal to the 
difference between the semicircle on AB and the sum of the 
semicircles on AN, NB, i.e. is equal to the area of the 0/0/817X09. 



Proposition 5. 

Let AB be the diameter of a semicircle, C any point on AB, 
and CD perpendicular to it, and let semicircles be described 
within the first semicircle and having AC, CB as diameters. 
Then, if two circles be drawn touching CD on different sides 
and each touching two of the semicircles^ the circles so drawn 
mil be equal. 

Let one of the circles touch CD at E, the semicircle on AB 
in F, and the semicircle on AC in G. 

Draw the diameter EH of the circle, which will accordingly 
be perpendicular to CD and therefore parallel to AB 

Join FH, HA, and FE> EB. Then, by Prop. 1, FffA, FEB 
are both straight lines, since EH, AB are parallel. 

For the same reason AGE, C6H are straight lines. 

Let AF produced meet CD in D, and let AE produced 
meet the outer semicircle in 7. Join BI, ID. 

H. A. 20 



306 ARCHIMEDES 

Then, since the angles AFB, ACD are right, the straight 
lines AD, AB are such that the perpendiculars on each from the 
extremity of the other meet in the point E. Therefore, by the 
properties of triangles, AE is perpendicular to the line joining 
B to D. 




But AE is perpendicular to BI. 
Therefore BID is a straight line. 

Now, since the angles at G, I are right, CH is parallel 
to BD. 

Therefore A B : BC = A D : DH 

= AC : HE, 

so that AC . CB = AB . HE. 

In like manner, if d is the diameter of the other circle, we can 
prove that AC . CB = AB . d. 

Therefore d = HE, and the circles are equal*. 

* The property upon which this result depends, viz. that 
AB:BC=AC:HE, 

appears as an intermediate step in a proposition of Pappus (p. 280, ed. Hultsch) 
which proves that, in the figure above, 



The truth of the latter proposition is easily seen. For, since the angle CEH 
is a right angle, and EG is perpendicular to CH, 

CE*:EH*=CG: OH 
=AC : HE. 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 307 

[As pointed out by an Arabian Scholiast Alkauhi, this 
proposition may be stated more generally. If, instead of one 
point on AB, we have two points C, D t and semicircles be 
described on AC, BD as diameters, and if, instead of the 
perpendicular to AB through C, we take the radical axis of the 
two semicircles, then the circles described on different sides of 
the radical axis and each touching it as well as two of the 
semicircles are equal. The proof is similar and presents no 
difficulty.] 



Proposition 6. 

Let AB, the diameter of a semicircle, be divided at C so that 
AC=%CB [or in any ratio]. Describe semicircles within the 
first semicircle and on AC, GB as diameters, and suppose a 
circle drawn touching all three semicircles. If GH be the 
diameter of this circle, to find the relation between GH and AB. 

Let GH be that diameter of the circle which is parallel to 
AB t and let the circle touch the semicircles on AB, AC, CB 
in D, E, F respectively. 

Join AG, GD and BE, HD. Then, by Prop. 1, AGD, BED 
are straight lines. 




For a like reason AEE, BFG are straight lines, as also 
are CEG, CFH. 

Let AD meet the semicircle on AC in 7, and let BD meet 
the semicircle on CB in K. Join CI, CK meeting AE, BF 

202 



308 



ARCHIMEDES 



respectively in L, M, and let QL, HM produced meet AB in 
N, P respectively. 

Now, in the triangle AGC, the perpendiculars from A, on 
the opposite sides meet in L. Therefore, by the properties of 
triangles, OLNis perpendicular to AC. 

Similarly HMP is perpendicular to CB. 

Again, since the angles at /, K, D are right, CK is parallel 
to AD, and CI to BD. 

Therefore AC:CB = AL: LH 

= AN:NP, 
BC:CA=BM:MG 
= BP:PN. 
AN:NP = NP: PB, 
or AN, NP, PB are in continued proportion*. 
Now, in the case where AC | CB, 



and 



Hence 



whence BP : PN : NA : AB = 4 : 6 : 9 : 19. 
Therefore GH = NP = & AB. 

And similarly GH can be found when AC : CB is equal to 
any other given ratiof. 

* This same property appears incidentally in Pappus (p. 226) as an inter- 
mediate step in the proof of the " ancient proposition " alluded to below. 

t In general, if AC : CB=\ : 1, we have 

BP:PN:NA: AB = l : X : X a : (1 + X+V), 
and GH:AB = \: (1 + X+X 2 ). 

It may be interesting to add the enunciation of the "ancient proposition" 
stated by Pappus (p. 208) and proved by him after several auxiliary lemmas. 




BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



809 



Proposition 7. 

If circles be circumscribed about and inscribed in a square, 
the circumscribed circle is double of the inscribed circle. 

For the ratio of the circumscribed to the inscribed circle is 
equal to that of the square on the diagonal to the square itself, 
i.e. to the ratio 2 : 1. 

Proposition 8. 

If A B be any chord of a circle whose centre is 0, and if AB 
be produced to C so that BG is equal to the radius; if further GO 
meet the circle in D and be produced to meet the circle a second 
time in E, the arc AE will be equal to three times the arc BD. 




Draw the chord EF parallel to AB, and join OB, OF. 

Let an otp^Xos be formed by three semicircles on AB, AC, CB as diameters, and 
let a series of circles be described, the first of which touches all three semicircles, 
while the second touches the first and two of the semicircles forming one end 
of the &p0i?Xo$, the third touches the second and the same two semicircles, and 
so on. Let the diameters of the successive circles be d^ d a , d,,... their centres 
Oj, 2 , O 3 ,... and O 1 N l) 0^, 3 iV s ,... the perpendiculars from the centres on 
AB. Then it is to be proved that 



310 



ARCHIMEDES 



Then, since the angles OEF, OFE are equal, 
*COF = 2tOEF 

= 2 ^ BCO, by parallels, 

= ZBOD, since BG 
Therefore 



so that the arc BF is equal to three times the arc BD. 

Hence the arc AE> which is equal to the arc BF, is equal to 
three times the arc BD*. 



Proposition 9. 

If in a circle two chords AB, CD which do not pass through 
the centre intersect at right angles, then 

(arc AD) + (arc CB) = (arc AC) + (arc DB). 

Let the chords intersect at 0, and draw the diameter EF 
parallel to AB intersecting CD in 
H. EF will thus bisect CD at 
right angles in H, and 

(arc #)=== (arc J<7). 
Also EDF, ECF are semi- 
circles, while 

(arc ED) = (arc EA) + (arc AD). 
Therefore 

(sum of arcs CF, EA, AD) = (arc 
of a semicircle). 

And the arcs AE, BF are equal. 
Therefore 

(arc CB) + (arc AD) = (arc of a semicircle). 

* This proposition gives a method of reducing the trisection of any angle, 
i.e. of any circular arc, to a problem of the kind known as vctaei*. Suppose that 
AE is the arc to be trisected, and that ED is the diameter through E of the circle 
of which AE is an arc. In order then to find an arc equal to one-third of AE, 
we have only to draw through A a line ADC, meeting the circle again in B and 
ED produced in C, such that BC it equal to the radius of the circle. For a 
discussion of this and other ve&rctt see the Introduction, Chapter V. 




BOOK OF LEMMAS 



311 



Hence the remainder of the circumference, the sum of the 
arcs A C t DB y is also equal to a semicircle; and the proposition 
is proved. 

Proposition 1O. 

Suppose that TA, TB are two tangents to a circle, while TC 
cuts it. Let BD be the chord through B parallel to TC, and let 
AD meet TC in E. Then, if EH be drawn perpendicular to BD 9 
it will bisect it in H. 

Let AB meet TC in F, and join BE. 

Now the angle TAB is equal to the angle in the alternate 
segment, i.e. 



= Z AST, by parallels. 




Hence the triangles EAT, AFT have one angle equal and 
another (at T) common. They are therefore similar, and 

FT:AT = AT:ET. 
Therefore 

ET . TF = TA 9 



It follows that the triangles EBT, BFT are similar. 
Therefore Z TEB = Z TBF 



But the angle TEB is equal to the angle EBD, and the 
angle TAB was proved equal to the angle EDB. 



312 



ARCHIMEDES 



Therefore 

And the angles at H are right angles. 

It follows that 



Proposition 11. 

If two chords AB, CD in a circle intersect at right angles in 
a point 0, not being the centre, then 

A0* + BO* + CO 9 + DO 8 - (diameter)*. 
Draw the diameter CE, and join AC, CJS, AD, BE. 

Then the angle OAO is equal 
to the angle CEB in the same seg- 
ment, and the angles AOC, EBC 
are right; therefore the triangles 
AOC, EBC are similar, and 




It follows that the subtended 
arcs, and therefore the chords AD, 
BE, are equal. 

* The figure of this proposition curiously recalls the figure of a problem 
given by Pappus (pp. 836-8) among his lemmas to the first Book of the treatise 
of Apollonius On Contacts (irepi lirajuv). The problem is, Given a circle and 
two points E, F (neither of which is necessarily, as in this case, the middle 
point of the chord of the circle drawn through E, F), to draw through E, F 
respectively two chords AD, AB Jwving a common extremity A and such that DB 
is parallel to EP. The analysis is as follows. Suppose the problem solved, BD 
being parallel to FE. Let BT, the tangent at B, meet EF produced in T. (T 
is not in general the pole of AB, so that TA is not generally the tangent at A.) 

Then / TBF= L BDA, in the alternate segment, 

= L AET, by parallels. 
Therefore A, E, B, T are concyclio, and 

EF.FT=AF.FB. 

But, the circle ADB and the point F being given, the rectangle AF . FB is given. 
Also EF is given. 

Hence FT is known. 

Thus, to make the construction, we have only to find the length of FT from 
the data, produce EF to T BO that FT has the ascertained length, draw the 
tangent TB, and then draw BD parallel to EF. DE, BF will then meet in A on 
the circle and will be the chords required. 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



313 



Thus 



(AO* + DO 9 ) + (50* + CO') = AD* 



Proposition 12. 

If AB be ike diameter of a semicircle, and TP, TQ the 
tangents to it from any point T, and if AQ, BP be joined 
meeting in R, then TR is perpendicular to AB. 

Let TR produced meet AB in M, and join PA, QB. 

Since the angle APB is right, 

Z PA B + Z PBA = (a right angle) 



.-70 







Add to each side the angle RBQ t and 

Z PAB + ^ QBA - (exterior) Z PJKQ. 

But ^ 2!PfZ = ^ PAB t and z TQE = 
in the alternate segments ; 
therefore z rP/J + z JQB = ^ PRQ. 

It follows from this that TP=TQ = TR. 

[For, if PT be produced to so that TO = TQ, we have 



And, by hypothesis, z P12Q 
By addition, t POQ -h ^ P12Q 



TPR + TQR 
TP/Z 4- OQ12. 



314 



ARCHIMEDES 



It follows that, in the quadrilateral OPRQ, the opposite 
angles are together equal to two right angles. Therefore a 
circle will go round OPQR, and T is its centre, because 
TO = TQ. Therefore TR = TP.] 



Thus /. TRP = z TPR = ^ PA M. 

Adding to each the angle PRM, 

Z. PAM+t PRM=t TRP + z PRM 

= (two right angles). 

Therefore ^ APR + Z ^13/jB = (two right angles), 
whence Z AMR = (a right angle)*. 



Proposition 13. 

If a diametw AB of a circle meet any chord CD, not a 
diameter, in E, and if AM, BN be drawn perpendicular to CD, 
then 



Let be the centre of the 
circle, and OH perpendicular to 
CD. Join BM, and produce HO to 
meet BM in K. 

Then CH=HD. 
And, by parallels, 



snce 



OA, 




NH=HM. 



Therefore 
Accordingly 



* TM is of course the polar of the intersection of PQ, AB, as it is the line 
joining the poles of PQ, AB respectively. 

t This proposition is of course true whether M, N lie on CD or on CD 
produced each way. Pappus proves it for the latter case in his first lemma 
(p. 788) to the second Book of Apollonius' 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 



315 



Proposition 14. 

Let AGE be a semicircle on AB as diameter, and let AD, 
BE be equal lengths measured along ABfrom A, B respectively. 
On AD, BE as diameters describe semicircles on the side towards 
C, and on DE as diameter a semicircle on the opposite side. Let 
the perpendicular to AB through 0, the centre of the first semi- 
circle, meet the opposite semicircles in C, F respectively. 

Then shall the area of the figure bounded by the circumferences 
of all the semicircles ("which Archimedes calls 'Salinvn'"*) be 
equal to the area of the circle on CF as diameter-^. 

By Eucl. n. 10, since ED is bisected at and produced 
to A, 

EA* + AD* = 2 (EO* + OA*) 9 

and CF=OA + OE = EA. 




* For the explanation of this name see note attached to the remarks on the 
Liber Assumptorum in the Introduction, Chapter II. On the grounds there 
given at length I believe <rd\ivov to be simply a Qraecised form of the Latin 
word salinum, 'salt-cellar.* 

t Cantor (Qesch. d. Mathematik, i. p. 285) compares this proposition 
with Hippocrates' attempt to square the circle by means of lunes, bat 
points out that the object of Archimedes may have been the converse of that 
of Hippocrates. For, whereas Hippocrates wished to find the area of a circle 
from that of other figures of the same sort, Archimedes* intention was possibly 
to equate the area of figures bounded by different curves to that of a circle 
regarded as already known. 



316 ARCHIMEDES 

Therefore 

Aff + DE* - 4 (EO* + OA*) 

But circles (and therefore semicircles) are to one another as 
the squares on their radii (or diameters). 

Therefore 
(sum of semicircles on AB, DE) 

= (circle on CF) + (sum of semicircles on AD, BE). 
Therefore 

(area of ' salinon ') = (area of circle on CF as diam.). 

Proposition 15. 

Let AB be the diameter of a circle, AC a side of an in- 
scribed regular pentagon, D the middle point of the arc AC. 
Join CD and produce it to meet BA produced in E; join AC, 
DB meeting in F, and draw FM perpendicular to AB. Then 

EM = (radius of circle)*. 

Let be the centre of the circle, and join DA, DM, DO, 
CB. 

Now Z A BC = f (right angle), 

and Z A BD = ^ DBG = (right angle), 

whence /L A OD = (right angle). 

* Pappus gives (p. 418) a proposition almost identical with this among the 
lemmas required for the comparison of the five regular polyhedra. His enunci- 
ation is substantially as follows. If DH be half the side of a pentagon inscribed 
in a circle, while DH is perpendicular to the radius OH A, and if HM be made 
equal to AH, then OA is divided at M in extreme and mean ratio, OM being the 
greater segment. 

In the course of the proof it is first shown that AD, DM, MO are all equal, 
as in the proposition above. 

Then, the triangles ODA, DAM being similar, 
OA:AD = AD:AM, 
or (since AD= OM) OA : OM= OM : MA. 



BOOK OF LEMMAS. 317 

Further, the triangles FOB, FMB are equal in all respects. 

Therefore, in the triangles DOB, DMB, the sides CB, ME 
being equal and BD common, while the angles CBD, MBD are 
equal, 

Z BCD / B MD = (right angle). 




But Z BCD + Z BAD = (two right angles) 



so that Z DAE 

and ZJ54D 

Therefore AD = MD. 

Now, in the triangle DJtfO, 

Z MOD = (right angle), 
Z ZX = f (right angle). 
Therefore Z ODJf = (right angle) = 4 OD ; 
whence OM=MD. 

Again Z #D.4 = (supplement of A DC) 



f (right angle) 



318 ARCHIMEDES 

Therefore, in the triangles EDA, ODM, 



and the sides AD 9 MD are equal. 

Hence the triangles are equal in all respects, and 



Therefore 



Moreover DE DO; and it follows that, since DE is equal 
to the side of an inscribed hexagon, and DC is the side of an 
inscribed decagon, EC is divided at D in extreme and mean 
ratio [i.e. EC : ED = ED : DC] ; "and this is proved in the 
book of the Elements." [Eucl. xin. 9, "If the side of the 
hexagon and the side of the decagon inscribed in the same 
circle be put together, the whole straight line is divided in 
extreme and mean ratio, and the greater segment is the 
side of the hexagon."] 


            -->
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
