<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Sand-Reckoner</title>
                <author>Archimedes</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Thomas Heath</persName>
                    <resp>translator</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>This electronic edition was prepared by Neel Smith, and is licensed under the
                    Creative Commons NonCommercial ShareAlike 3.0 License. Its markup validates
                    against version P5 of the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines, and follows the
                    markup conventions of the "Free Greek" project.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This text is based on pages 221-232 of the Dover reprint edition of Heath's
                    original 1897 publication now in the public domain: <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>Thomas Heath</editor>
                            <title>The Works of Archimedes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mineola, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dover</publisher>
                                <date>2002</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope
                                type="pp">221-232</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- 
            

THE SAND-RECKONER. 



" THERE are some, king Gelon, who think that the number 
of the sand is infinite in multitude ; and I mean by the sand 
not only that which exists about Syracuse and the rest of Sicily 
but also that which is found in every region whether inhabited 
or uninhabited. Again there are some who, without regarding 
it as infinite, yet think that no number has been named which 
is great enough to exceed its multitude. And it is clear that 
they who hold this view, if they imagined a mass made up of 
sand in other respects as large as the mass of the earth, in- 
cluding in it all the seas and the hollows of the earth filled up 
to a height equal to that of the highest of the mountains, 
would be many times further still from recognising that any 
number could be expressed which exceeded the multitude of 
the sand so taken. But I will try to show you by means of 
geometrical proofs, which you will be able to follow, that, of the 
numbers named by me and given in the work which I sent to 
Zeuxippus, some exceed not only the number of the mass of 
sand equal in magnitude to the earth filled up in the way 
described, but also that of a mass equal in magnitude to the 
universe. Now you are aware that 'universe* is the name 
given by most astronomers to the sphere whose centre is the 
centre of the earth and whose radius is equal to the straight 
line between the centre of the sun and the centre of the earth. 
This is the common account (TO, ypa^opeva), as you have heard 
from astronomers. But Aristarchus of Samos brought out a 



222 ARCHIMEDES 

book consisting of some hypotheses, in which the premisses lead 
to the result that the universe is many times greater than that 
now so called. His hypotheses are that the fixed stars and the 
sun remain unmoved, that the earth revolves about the sun in 
the circumference of a circle, the sun lying in the middle of the 
orbit, and that the sphere of the fixed stars, situated about the 
same centre as the sun, is so great that the circle in which he 
supposes the earth to revolve bears such a proportion to the 
distance of the fixed stars as the centre of the sphere bears to 
its surface. Now it is easy to see that this is impossible ; for, 
since the centre of the sphere has no magnitude, we cannot 
conceive it to bear any ratio whatever to the surface of the 
sphere. We must however take Aristarchus to mean this: 
since we conceive the earth to be, as it were, the centre of 
the universe, the ratio which the earth bears to what we 
describe as the ' universe ' is the same as the ratio which the 
sphere containing the circle in which he supposes the earth to 
revolve bears to the sphere of the fixed stars. For he adapts 
the proofs of his results to a hypothesis of this kind, and in 
particular he appears to suppose the magnitude of the sphere 
in which he represents the earth as moving to be equal to what 
we call the ' universe/ 

I say then that, even if a sphere were made up of the sand, 
as great as Aristarchus supposes the sphere of the fixed stars 
to be, I shall still prove that, of the numbers named in the 
Principles*) some exceed in multitude the number of the 
sand which is equal in magnitude to the sphere referred to, 
provided that the following assumptions be made. 

1. The perimeter of the earth is about 3,000,000 stadia and 
not greater. 

It is true that some have tried, as you are of course aware, 
to prove that the said perimeter is about 300,000 stadia. But 
I go further and, putting the magnitude of the earth at ten 
times the size that my predecessors thought it, I suppose its 
perimeter to be about 3,000,000 stadia and not greater. 

* 'Apxal was apparently the title of the work sent to Zeuxippus. Of. the 
note attached to the enumeration of lost works of Archimedes in the Introduction, 
Chapter II., ad fin. 



THE SAND-RECKONER. 223 

2. The diameter of the earth is greater than the diameter of 
the moon, and the diameter of the sun is greater than the diameter 
of tlte earth. 

In this assumption I follow most of the earlier astronomers. 

3. The diameter of the sun is about 30 times the diameter of 
the moon and not greater, 

It is true that, of the earlier astronomers, Eudoxus declared 
it to be about nine times as great, and Pheidias my father* 
twelve times, while Aristarchus tried to prove that the diameter 
of the sun is greater than 18 times but less than 20 times the 
diameter of the moon. But I go even further than Aristarchus, 
in order that the truth of my proposition may be established 
beyond dispute, and I suppose the diameter of the sun to be 
about 30 times that of the moon and not greater. 

4. The diameter of the sun is greater than the side of the 
chiliagon inscribed in the greatest circle in the (sphere of the} 
universe. 

I make this assumption f because Aristarchus discovered 
that the sun appeared to be about y^^th part of the circle of 
the zodiac, and I myself tried, by a method which I will now 
describe, to find experimentally (opyavitcoSs) the angle sub- 
tended by the sun and having its vertex at the eye (rdv ywviav, 
et? av o aXio? eVap/Aofefc rdv /copv<f>dv e^oucrai/ Trem ra ctyei)." 

[Up to this point the treatise has been literally translated 
because of the historical interest attaching to the ipsissima 
verba of Archimedes on such a subject. The rest of the work 
can now be more freely reproduced, and, before proceeding to 
the mathematical contents of it, it is only necessary to remark 
that Archimedes next describes how he arrived at a higher and 
a lower limit for the angle subtended by the sun. This he did 

* rou cl/AoO irarp6s is the correction of Blass for roO 'Affoibrarpo? (Jahrb. f. 
Philol. cxxvii. 1883). 

t This is not, strictly speaking, an assumption ; it is a proposition proved 
later (pp. 2246) by means of the result of an experiment about to be 
described. 



224 ARCHIMEDES 

by taking a long rod or ruler (*ai/a>i/), fastening on the end of it 
a small cylinder or disc, pointing the rod in the direction of the 
sun just after its rising (so that it was possible to look directly 
at it), then putting the cylinder at such a distance that it just 
concealed, and just failed to conceal, the sun, and lastly measur- 
ing the angles subtended by the cylinder. He explains also the 
correction which he thought it necessary to make because " the 
eye does not see from one point but from a certain area " (eVel 
al oyfrie? ov/c a<* evos cra/jLiov /SXeTroi/n, d\\d OTTO TWOS 



The result of the experiment was to show that the angle 
subtended by the diameter of the sun was less than T ^th part, 
and greater than ^th part, of a right angle. 

To prove that (on this assumption) the diameter of the sun 
is greater than the side of a chiliagon, or figure with 1000 equal 
sides, inscribed in a great circle of the ' universe.' 

Suppose the plane of the paper to be the plane passing 
through the centre of the sun, the centre of the earth and the 
eye, at the time when the sun has just risen above the horizon. 
Let the plane cut the earth in the circle EHL and the sun 
in the circle FKG, the centres of the earth and sun being (7, 
respectively, and E being the position of the eye. 

Further, let the plane cut the sphere of the * universe ' (i.e. 
the sphere whose centre is C and radius GO) in the great 
circle AOB. 

Draw from E two tangents to the circle FKG touching it 
at P, Q, and from C draw two other tangents to the same circle 
touching it in F t G respectively. 

Let CO meet the sections of the earth and sun in H, K 
respectively; and let OF, CG produced meet the great circle 
AOB in A, B. 

Join EO, OF, OG, OP, OQ, AB, and let AB meet CO in M. 
Now CO > EO, since the sun is just above the horizon. 
Therefore ^ PEQ > Z FCG. 



And tPEQ> 
but < 



THE BAND-RECKONER. 225 

R represents a right angle. 




Thus Z FOG < ^R, a fortiori, 

and the chord AB subtends an arc of the great circle which is 



less than ^^th of the circumference of that circle, i.e. 

A B < (side of 656-sided polygon inscribed in the circle). 

Now the perimeter of any polygon inscribed in the great 
circle is less than tyCO. [Of. Measurement of a circle, Prop. 3.] 

Therefore AB : C0<ll: 1148, 

and, a fortiori, AB < ^faCO ........................ (a). 

Again, since OA = CO, and A M is perpendicular to CO, 
while OF is perpendicular to CA, 

AM=OF. 

Therefore AB = 2AM = (diameter of sun). 
Thus (diameter of sun) < ^00, by (a), 

and, a fortiori, 

(diameter of earth) < jfaCO. [Assumption 2] 



H. A. 



15 



226 ARCHIMEDES 

Hence 
so that 

or CO :HK<100:99. 

And CO>CF, 

while HK<EQ. 

Therefore CF : EQ<IW : 99 

Now in the right-angled triangles CFO t EQO, of the sides 
about the right angles, 

OF- OQ, but EQ < CF (since EO < CO). 
Therefore Z OEQ : Z OCF > CO : EO, 

but < OF : 

Doubling the angles, 



< 100 : 99, by () above. 

But Z PEQ > vfaR, by hypothesis. 

Therefore Z A CB > 3$^ R 



It follows that the arc AB is greater than ^th of the circum- 
ference of the great circle A OB. 

Hence, a fortiori, 

AB > (side of chiliagon inscribed in great circle), 
and AB is equal to the diameter of the sun, as proved above. 



The following results can now be proved : 

(diameter of ' universe') < 10,000 (diameter of earth), 
and (diameter of 'universe') < 10,000,000,000 stadia. 

* The proposition here assumed is of course equivalent to the trigonometrical 
formula which states that, if a, /3 are the circular measures of two angles, each 
less than a right angle, of which a is the greater, then 

tan a a sin a 
/ > sin/? ' 



THE SAND-RECKONER. 227 

(1) Suppose, for brevity, that d u represents the diameter 
of the ' universe/ d 8 that of the sun, d e that of the earth, and d m 
that of the moon. 

By hypothesis, d s ^ 30d m , [Assumption 3] 

and d e > d m ; [Assumption 2] 

therefore d s < 3Qd e . 

Now, by the last proposition, 

d 8 > (side of chiliagon inscribed in great circle), 
so that (perimeter of chiliagon) < lOOOc?* 

< 30,000d e . 

But the perimeter of any regular polygon with more sides 
than 6 inscribed in a circle is greater than that of the inscribed 
regular hexagon, and therefore greater than three times the 
diameter. Hence 

(perimeter of chiliagon) > 3d tt . 

It follows that d u < 10,000d e . 

(2) (Perimeter of earth) ^ 3,000,000 stadia. 

[Assumption 1] 
and (perimeter of earth) > Sd e . 

Therefore d e < 1,000,000 stadia, 

whence d u < 10,000,000,000 stadia. 



Assumption 5. 

Suppose a quantity of sand taken not greater than a poppy- 
seed, and suppose that it contains not more than 10,000 grains. 

Next suppose the diameter of the poppy-seed to be not less 
than ^th of a finger-breadth. 

Orders and periods of numbers. 

I. We have traditional names for numbers up to a 
myriad (10,000); we can therefore express numbers up to a 
myriad myriads (100,000,000). Let these numbers be called 
numbers of the first order. 

Suppose the 100,000,000 to be the unit of the second order, 
and let the second order consist of the numbers from that unit 
up to (100,000,000)'. 

152 



228 ARCHIMEDES 

Let this again be the unit of the third order of numbers 
ending with (100,000,000)*; and so on, until we reach the 
100,000,000^ order of numbers ending with (lOO^OO.OOO) 100 ' 000 ' 000 , 
which we will call P. 

II. Suppose the numbers from 1 to P just described to 
form the first period. 

Let P be the unit of the first order of the second period, and . 
let this consist of the numbers from P up to 100,000,000 P. 

Let the last number be the unit of the second order of the 
second period, and let this end with (100,000,000)* P. 

We can go on in this way till we reach the 100,000,000& order 
of the second period ending with (100,000,000)**^, or P*. 

III. Taking P 8 as the unit of the first order of the third 
period, we proceed in the same way till we reach the 
100,000,000tfi order of the third period ending with P 8 . 

IV. Taking P 8 as the unit of the first order of the fourth 
period, we continue the same process until we arrive at the 
100,000,000*& order of the 100,000,000/i period ending with 
pioo,ooo,ooo ihi g last number is expressed by Archimedes as " a 
myriad-myriad units of the myriad-myriad-th order of the 
myriad-myriad-th period (al p,vpiaici<Fp t vpt,oa"ra<i TrepioSov /j,vpia- 
fcia-^vpio(Trv apiO^v pvplai, pvpidSes)" which is easily seen 

to be 100,000,000 times the product of (lOO.OOO^OO)"' 999 ' 999 and 
i e pioo,ooo,ow 



[The scheme of numbers thus described can be exhibited 
more clearly by means of indices as follows. 

FIRST PERIOD. 

First order. Numbers from 1 to 10 8 . 
Second order. 10 8 to 10 16 . 
Third order. 10" to 10 24 . 



order. lO 8 -* 108 - 1 ' to 10 8 - 10 " (P, say). 



THE SAND-RECKONER. 229 

SECOND PERIOD. 

First order. Numbers from P.I to P .IV. 
Second order. P . 10 8 to P . 10". 



(W)th order. P.IO 8 -*" 8 - 1 ) to 

P.10 8 - 108 (or P 1 ). 



(10 8 )TH PERIOD. 

First order. P 108 - 1 . 1 to P 108 - 1 . 10*. 

Second order. P 108 - 1 . 10 8 to P 108 - 1 . 1<K 



(10*)th order. P^-MO 8 -^ 8 - 1 * to 

P" 8 -!. lOs.io" (i.e. P 108 ). 

The prodigious extent of this scheme will be appreciated 
when it is considered that the last number in the first period 
would be represented now by 1 followed by 800,000,000 ciphers, 
while the last number of the (W*)th period would require 
100,000,000 times as many ciphers, i.e. 80,000 million millions 
of ciphers.] 

Octads. 

Consider the series of terms in continued proportion of 
which the first is 1 and the second 10 [i.e. the geometrical 
progression 1, 10 1 , 10 2 , 10 s , ...]. The first octad of these terms 
[i.e. 1, 10 1 , 10*, ...10 7 ] fall accordingly under the first order 
of the first period above described, the second octad [i.e. 
10 8 , 10 fl , ... 10 16 ] under the second order of the first period, the 
first term of the octad being the unit of the corresponding 
order in each case. Similarly for the third octad, and so on. 
We can, in the same way, place any number of octads. 

Theorem. 

If there be any number of terms of a series in continued 
proportion, say A l9 A 3 , A 9 ,... A m ,... A n ,... An+n^,... of which 
A l ^ 1, J[ a = 10 [so that the series forms the geometrical pro- 
gression 1, 10 1 , 10 a ,...10 wl - 1 ,...10 n - 1 ,...10 M+f| - a ,...], and if any 
two terms as A m , A n be taken and multiplied, the product 



230 ARCHIMEDES 

A m . A n mil be a term in the same series and will be as many 
terms distant from A n as A m is distant from A l ; also it mil be 
distant from A l by a number of terms less by one than the sum 
of the numbers of terms by which A m and A n respectively are 
distant from A^ 

Take the term which is distant from A n by the same 
number of terms as A m is distant from A l9 This number of 
terms is m (the first and last being both counted). Thus the 
term to be taken is m terms distant from A n , and is therefore 
the term A m+n ^. 

We have therefore to prove that 

Now terms equally distant from other terms in the con- 
tinued proportion are proportional. 

A A 

Thus * = m+n "" 1 

AI A n 

But A m = A m .A l , since A l = 1. 

Therefore A m + n _ 1 A m . A n (1). 

The second result is now obvious, since A m is m terms 
distant from A l9 A n is n terms distant from A l9 and A m+n ^ is 
(m 4- n 1) terms distant from -4^ 

Application to the number of the sand. 

By Assumption 5 [p. 227], 

(diam. of poppy-seed) ^ ^ (finger-breadth); 

and, since spheres are to one another in the triplicate ratio 
of their diameters, it follows that 

(sphere of diam. 1 finger-breadth) ^ 64,000 poppy-seeds 

> 64,000 x 10,000 
} 640,000,000 

^6 units of second grains 
order + 40,000,000 V of 
units of first order sand, 
(a fortiori) < 10 units of second 
order of numbers. 



THE SAND-RECKONER. 



231 



We now gradually increase the diameter of the supposed 
sphere, multiplying it by 100 each time. Thus, remembering 
that the sphere is thereby multiplied by 100* or 1,000,000, the 
number of grains of sand which would be contained in a sphere 
with each successive diameter may be arrived at as follows. 



Diameter of sphere. 
(1) 100 finger-breadths 



(2) 10,000 finger-breadths 



(3) 1 stadium 

(< 10,000 finger-breadths) 

(4) 100 stadia 



(5) 10,000 stadia 



(6) 1,000,000 stadia 



(7) 100,000,000 stadia 



(8) 10,000,000,000 stadia 



Corresponding number of grains of sand. 

< 1,000,000 x 10 units of second order 
<(7th term of series) x (10th term of 

series) 

< 16th term of series [i.e. 10 16 ] 
<[10 7 or] 10,000,000 units of the second 

order. 

< 1,000,000 x (last number) 

< (7th term of series) x (16th term) 

< 22nd term of series [i.e. 10 21 ] 

< [10 6 or] 100,000 units of third order. 

< 100,000 units of third order. 

* 

< 1,000,000 x (last number) 

< (7th term of series) x (22nd term) 

< 28th term of series [10 27 ] 
<[103 or] 1,000 units of fourth order. 

< 1,000,000 x (last number) 

< (7th term of series) x (28th term) 

< 34th term of series [10 33 ] 

< 10 units of fifth order. 

< (7th term of series) x (34th term) 

< 40th term [10 39 ] 
<[10 T or] 10,000,000 units of fifth order. 

< (7th term of series) x (40th term) 

< 46th term [10* 6 ] 
<[10 6 or] 100,000 units of sixth order. 

< (7th term of series) x (46th term) 

< 52nd term of series [10 61 ] 

< [10 3 or] 1,000 units of seventh order. 



But, by the proposition above [p. 227], 

(diameter of universe ') < 10,000,000,000 stadia. 

Hence the number of grains of sand which could be contained 
in a sphere of the size of our 'universe' is less than 1,000 units 
of the seventh order of numbers [or 10 51 ]. 



232 ARCHIMEDES 

From this we can prove further that a sphere of the size 
attributed by Aristarchus to the sphere of the fixed stars would 
contain a number of grains of sand less than 10,000,000 units 
of the eighth order of numbers [or lO** 7 = 10"]. 

For, by hypothesis, 

(earth) : (' universe ') = (' universe ') : (sphere of fixed stars). 
And [p. 227] 

(diameter of ' universe ') < 10,000 (diam. of earth) ; 
whence 

(diam. of sphere of fixed stars) < 10,000 (diam. of ' universe '). 
Therefore 

(sphere of fixed stars) < (10,000) 8 . (' universe '). 
It follows that the number of grains of sand which would be 
contained in a sphere equal to the sphere of the fixed stars 

< (10,000)' x 1,000 units of seventh order 

< (13th term of series) x (52nd term of series) 

< 64th term of series [i.e. 10 63 ] 

< [10 7 or] 10,000,000 units of eighth order of numbers. 

Conclusion. 

"I conceive that these things, king Gelon, will appear 
incredible to the great majority of people who have not studied 
mathematics, but that to those who are conversant therewith 
and have given thought to the question of the distances and 
sizes of the earth the sun and moon and the whole universe the 
proof will carry conviction. And it was for this reason that 
I thought the subject would be not inappropriate for your 
consideration." 


            -->
            <p/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
